<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>[Certein workes of blessed Cipriane the martyr, translated out of laten by J. Scory]</title>
            <author>Cyprian, Saint, Bishop of Carthage.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1556</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 52 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69169</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6152</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111012</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846446</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846446</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11414</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69169)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11414)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 213:10, 880:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>[Certein workes of blessed Cipriane the martyr, translated out of laten by J. Scory]</title>
                  <author>Cyprian, Saint, Bishop of Carthage.</author>
                  <author>Scory, John, d. 1585.</author>
                  <author>Cyprian, Saint, Bishop of Carthage. De mortalitate.</author>
                  <author>Cyprian, Saint, Bishop of Carthage. Ad Fortunatum.</author>
                  <author>Cyprian, Saint, Bishop of Carthage. Epistola ad Thibaritanos.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[102+] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>E. van der Erve,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Emden :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1556]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint and title from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F G³+.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 6159.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 6159 on reel 213.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: lacks title page, and all after leaf G3.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at UMI microfilm, reels 213 (Bodleian copy) and reel 880.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11414:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11414:1"/>
            <head>A ſermon of bleſſed Cipriane touching mortalitie, exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the loue of forſating this lyfe: and ſhewing that notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the iuſte and vniuſte dye wyth out difference, yet no man ought to thynke, that the good &amp; euell come bothe to one deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as the iuſte are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led hence to refreſhing, and thouſuſte are caught awaye vnto puniſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment.</head>
            <p>ALthoughe ther be many of you moſt dearely beloued brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which haue a ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de mynde, a ſtedfaſt fayth, and a deuoute ſoule, which is not moued at this great mortalitie, but as a ſtrong and ſtable rocke dothe rather break the trobleſom aſſaultes, the violent and raging wafes of this worlde, it ſelfe beyng neither broken nor ouercome with temtacions, but only tried: Neuertheles becauſe I per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue that ther are certayne among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:11414:2"/>people,<note place="margin">The cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtancy and departing from true religion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> which eyther thorow the weak<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of mynde, or litelnes of faythe, or ſwetenes of wordly lyfe, or te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>derneſſe of kynde, or (which is worſe) thorowe thignoraunce of the truthe, ſtande not ſtedfaſtly, nor do put furth the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and the inuincible ſtrenght of their harte, this thing ought neither to be diſſembled nor to be kept in ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but that we (to the vttermoſt of our po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer) ſhould with full force, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des taken of the holy ſcripture, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and kepe downe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cowardnes, of the deintie mynde, &amp; that he which is now begonne to be the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God and of Chriſt, myght alſo be counted worthy of Chriſt. For he that is a ſoul diour to God moſt dearly beloued bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren, and beyng put in the celeſtiall tentes do now hope for heauenlye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes, ought to knowe him ſelfe: ſo that we ſhould in no wiſe either feare, or ſtaye for the ſtormes and whirle wyndes of the worlde: foraſmuche as the Lorde hathe tolde aforehande that theſe ſhould come, inſtructing and tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching with thexhortacion of his for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing voice, and preparing &amp; ſtrenght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the people of his churche, to all maner of ſuffering of thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges to come,
<pb facs="tcp:11414:2"/>hathe aforehande ſhewed and taught, that warres, and hongers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.</note> and earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes, &amp; peſtilences ſhould ſpring vp &amp; ariſe euery where. And that no ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne and newe feare of hurtful thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges ſhould violently ſhake vs, he hath beforehande warned that aduerſities and troubles ſhall growe vp thic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and thicker,<note place="margin">The laſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tymes ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trobleſum.</note> more and more in the laſt tymes. They do nowe happen loo, that were aforehande tolde: and foraſmuche as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinges do now hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen which were tolde aforehande, all thinges that are promiſed, ſhal alſo fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe after, by the promiſe of the Lord hymſelfe, which ſayeth: but whan ye ſhall ſee theſe thinges come to paſſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luc.</hi> 21.</note> knowe ye that the kingdome of God is at hande.<note place="margin">The king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God &amp; e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal life are at hand.</note> The kingdome of God dearely beloued brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beginneth to be at hande: the worlde paſſing away, the reward of lyfe, and ioye of eternal healthe, and the continuall gladneſſe and poſſeſſion of paradiſe lately loſte are eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now come: Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now do heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly thinges ſuccede earthy, great thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: lytell, and euerlaſting tranſitory and fading away. What place is here left for troble and carefulnes? Who amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g theſe thinges ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be fearful and
<pb facs="tcp:11414:3"/>ſorowful, except he wante both faith &amp; hope?<note place="margin">who feare deathe.</note> It is his ꝑt to fear death, which wil not go to Chriſt: it is his part to refuſe to go to Chriſt, which beleueth not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhal begin to reigne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Abac.</hi> 2.</note> For it is written that the rightful ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyueth by faythe. Yf thou be rightfull and lyueſt thorow faythe, yf thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leueſt truly in God, why doeſt thou not embrace and reioyce of this, that thou ſhalt be with Chriſt, &amp; be by the Lordes promiſe in ſaffetie, inaſmuche as thou art called to Chriſt, and dely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the deuell?<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luce.</hi> 2.</note> To be ſhorte that iuſte man Symeon that was a right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man in dede,<note place="margin">Thorowe faithe god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes are obſerued.</note> which thorow a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecte faith obſerued goddes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had receyued anſwer of God, that he ſhould not dye before he had ſen Chriſt: And whan the babe Chriſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his mother was come into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Temple, he knewe thorowe the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, that Chriſt of whome he was tolde before was nowe borne: whome after that he had ſene, he knewe that he ſhould ſhortly dye. He therfore being gladde of deathe that was now at hand, and fearing nothing his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling hence that was hardby, toke, the childe in his handes, and praiſid God and cried out, ſaing: O Lord now
<pb facs="tcp:11414:3"/>let thy ſeruant departe in peace ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to thy worde: For myne eyes haue ſene thy ſauyng healthe. In which wordes he proueth and teſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that than the ſeruauntes of God haue peace,<note place="margin">when and wheare we maye truſt to haue ſure reſt</note> and that than they haue free and quiet reſt, whan we beyng drawen out of the boiſtous tempeſtes of this worlde, attayne the hauen of eternall reſte and ſaffetie: wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this deathe beyng remoued, we come to immortalitie. For this is our pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, this is the reſte that a man maye truſte to, this is the ſtable, the ſure,<note place="margin">we haue here a con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynuall battaile againſt vices.</note> and perpetuall ſaffetye. Furthermore in the worlde what is ther elles, but a dayly fyght againſt the deuell? Howe hard, daungerous, and continuall, is this fyght againſt his dartes and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes? We muſt fyght againſt coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes, againſt vnclennes, againſt wrathe, againſt ambicion, againſt car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nall vices: our wraſtlyng with the flic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kering intiſementes of the worlde is laborious, continuall, and paynfull. The mynde of man beyng beſieged &amp; compaſſed in on euery ſyde with the aſſaultes of the deuel, dothe hardly re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiſte any temptation. Yf couetouſnes be throwen downe, luſte ryſeth vp.
<pb facs="tcp:11414:4"/>Yf luſt be ſuppreſſed, ambicion folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth, Yf ambicion be deſpiſed, wrathe bothe vexe, pride is puffed vp, dronke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe calleth in, enuye breaketh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde, zele cutteth of frendſhip. Thou arte compelled to curſe, which goddes lawe forbiddeth: thou art conſtrayned to ſweare, which is vnlawful. So ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s dothe the mynde day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuffer, with ſo many daungers is the harte dayly vexed, and dothe it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyte vs to ſtande here long among the deuelles ſwerdes: whan we ought ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to deſire and wiſhe by the meanes of a ſwift deathe, to make haſt to Chriſt? According as he inſtructed vs ſaieng: verely verely I ſaie vnto you, ye ſhall wepe and lament, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world ſhal reioyce: you ſhall be ſorowful, but your ſorowe ſhal be turned in to ioye. Who maketh not haſt to com vnto myrthe?<note place="margin">Ioan. <hi>18.</hi> Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence we go to mirthe &amp; ioye.</note> Who deſireth not to be w<hi rend="sup">c</hi>out ſorwe? but whan our heuynes ſhall be turned in to ioye, the Lord him ſelf declareth, ſaieng: I wil ſe you againe, and your harte ſhall reioice, and your ioye ſhall no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take from you. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuche than as the ſight of Chriſt is our ioie, neither can we haue any ioie, but whan we haue ſeen Chriſt: What
<pb facs="tcp:11414:4"/>blindneſſe or rather madnes of mynd is this, to loue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> troubles and paines and teares of the worlde, and not to make haſte to that ioye, that ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neuer be taken from vs? This thing happe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth dearely beloued brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">whi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e loue this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> liffe ſo moche.</note> bycauſe faythe is wanting, becauſe no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leueth the thinges to come, which God (that is true) hath promiſed, whoſe worde vnto them that beleue is euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting, and ſtable. Yf a ſage man and worthy prayſe dyd promiſe thee any thyng, thou woldeſt verely beleue his promyſe, neither woldeſt thou thynke to be deceyued and begyled of him, of whom thou art perſuaded, that he wil abyde by his wordes and dedes: but nowe God ſpeaketh vnto thee, &amp; doeſt thou vnfaythfull man wauer with an vnbeleuyng mynde? God doeth ꝓmiſe vnto the departing this worlde im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortalitie and eternal lyfe, and doeſt thou doubt? This is euen to be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God,<note place="margin">Howe p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitable a thing ye y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to depart oute of this world</note> this is thorowe the ſinne of vnbeleaue toffende Chriſt the maſtre of beleauing people: This is to be in the church and in the houſe of faithe, &amp; to be witout faithe: Howe profitable a thing it is to departe out of this worlde, Chriſt him ſelfe the
<pb facs="tcp:11414:5"/>maiſtre of our ſaluacion and profit ſheweth, which wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his diſciples war ſorowful bicauſe he ſaid that he ſhould now departe from them, ſpake unto them ſaieng:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 14.</note> Yf you loued me, ye wold reioyce, bicauſe I go to the father: Wherby he dothe teache and declare, that we ought rather to reioyce than to be ſorowfull, whan they whome we dearely loue departe this worlde. Of the which thing the bleſſed apoſtle Paule being mindeful, writeth in his epiſtle and ſaieth: Chriſt is liffe vnto me,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phi.</hi> 1.</note> and deathe aua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tage: He rekened it the chefeſt gaine to be now no more tyed with the ſnares of the worlde, to be now no more in daunger of any ſynnes and vices of the fleſhe, to be ridde of vexing trobles, and deliuered from the venemouſe iawes of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, and to go furthe at the calling of Chriſt vnto the ioye of eternal ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion. But ſom ar troubled, bicauſe the diſeaſe of this ſickenes do indiffere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come vpon our men, aſwell as vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the heathen: as though the chriſtean had beleaued to this ende, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might bothe be fre from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fealing of euelles, &amp; inioye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pleaſures of the worlde, &amp; not rather ſuffering here al maner of
<pb facs="tcp:11414:5"/>aduerſitie be reſerued and kept vnto the ioye to come. Some men ar trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled bicauſe this mortalitie &amp; deathe is common to vs alſo with other.<note place="margin">Trobles, ſickneſſes, &amp; deathe ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to all men</note> But what thing in this worlde haue not we common with other, ſo long as yet (according to thordenaunce of our furſt birthe) this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon fleſhe remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth? So long as we abide here in the worlde, in the equalite of fleſhe we ar ioyned together with mankinde, but in the ſpirite we ar ſeperated. Therfor vntil this corruptible maye put on in corruption,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.</note> and this mortal maye re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue unmortalitie, &amp; the ſpirite bring vs vnto God the father, we haue our parte in all maner of incommodities and diſpleaſures of the fleſhe common vnto mankinde. Thus wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de is barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thorowe an vnfruteful blaſt, hunger ſpareth no man. Thus whan any city is poſſeſſed throwe the inrode of thennemy, captiuite waſteth all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> together: And whan the ſtonyrocks burſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhipe in peces, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhipwracke is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon to al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaiie in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhipe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And the payne of thies, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ging agwes, &amp; the diſeaſe of al partes of the body ar common to vs with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, ſo long as we cary about this
<pb facs="tcp:11414:6"/>common fleſhe in the worlde. Yea ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yf the chriſtian man knewe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what condicion and what lawe he beleued,<note place="margin">The true chriſtian hathe moſt troble in this world</note> he ſhould knowe that he muſt be trobled in this world aboue other, which aboue other muſt wreſtle with thaſſaultes of the deuel. The ſcripture teacheth and warneth vs aforehande, ſayeng: My ſonne whan thou becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt goddes ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, ſtande in right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe and feare,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 2.</note> and prepare thy ſoule to temptacion. And agayne: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure in ſorowe and in feare, &amp; thorow hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>blenes haue thou pacience, for both golde and ſiluer are tryed by the fyre. Iob after the loſſe of his goodes, after the death of his children,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.</note> being thus greuouſly afflicted bothe with woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, and with vermine, was not ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, but tried: which in the ſelfe gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fes and ſorowes that he ſuffered, did declare the pacience of a godly minde, ſayeng: Naked came I out of my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe, naked alſo ſhal I go vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der thearthe, the Lorde gaue, and the Lorde hathe taken awaye: as it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Lorde, euen ſo hathe it happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, The Lordes name be bleſſed. And whan his wyfe wolde haue enforced him, that he being thorowe great ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe
<pb facs="tcp:11414:6"/>impacient, ſhould with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playning and malicious voice haue ſpoken ſomthing againſt God, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered her and ſayd: Thou haſt ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as one of the foliſhe wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iob.</hi> 2.</note> For yf we haue receyued proſperitie at the Lor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, why ſhould we not ſuffer ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie? In all theſe thinges that hap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pened vnto Iob, he ſynned nothing with his lippes in the preſence of the Lorde. Therfore the Lord beareth him witneſſe, ſayng: haſt thou marked my ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Iob, ther is not one lyke him vpon thearthe, a man without faute, a true worſhipper of God.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tobi.</hi> 1.</note> Tobias alſo after his noble workes, after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifolde and glorious comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacions of his mercie, did ſuffre the blindnes of eyes, and he fearing and prayſing God in aduerſitie, grewe vp to prayſe by the ſelfe plage of his body: whome his owne wyfe alſo aſſayed to corrupt ſaing: Where are thy rightfulneſſes become? loo what thou ſuffreſt. But he being ſtedfaſte and ſtable in the feare of God, and armed with a godly faith to ſuffre all maner of paſſions, gaue no place in his ſorowe, to the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion of his weake wyfe, but did tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the greater pacience procure the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:11414:7"/>fauoure of God: whom after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes the angel Raphael praiſed &amp; ſaid: Yt is an henorable thing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and praiſe the workes of God: For whan thou and thy daughter in lawe Sara did praie, I offred vp the remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of your praier, in the preſence of the glory of God: and whan thou didiſt ſimply burye the deade, and bicauſe thou delayedſt not to ariſe and to leaue thine owne dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar, and wenſt furthe and dideſt bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye the deade, I am ſent to trie thee. And againe he ſaieth: I am ſent to heale the,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tobi.</hi> 12.</note> &amp; thy daughter in lawe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra: For I am Raphael one of the .vij. holy angels, which doo ſtande and haue our conuerſacion before the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God. This ſufferance the iuſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue alwaies had, this diſcipline tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lordes ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce kept: not to murmur in aduerſitie, but paciently and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fully to receaue what ſo euer do happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this worlde. Wheras the Iuiſhe people hathe in this pointe alwaies offended, bicauſe they did often murmur againſt God, as the Lord God doeth witneſſe in the boke of nombres ſaieng:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Num.</hi> 20.</note> let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ceaſe to murmur againſt me, &amp; thei ſhal not
<pb facs="tcp:11414:7"/>dye. Wee maye not moſt deare bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren grudge in aduerſites, but quiet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly ſuffer what ſo euer ſhal happen, ſeing it is written: that a tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled ſpirite is a ſacrifice to God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.</note> and that God deſpiſeth not a contrite and an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble hart. In the Deuteronomy alſo the holy gooſt doeth warne vs by Moſes, and ſaieth:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deu.</hi> 8.</note> The Lord thy God ſhall vexe the, and ſhall throwe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger vpon the, and thine hart ſhall be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whether thou wilt truly kepe his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes or not. And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine he ſaieth: The Lord your God doeth tempte you, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he maie knowe, whether you loue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord your God w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al your harte, &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al your ſowle. Thus did Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pleaſe God:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gene.</hi> 22.</note> &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might ſo do, he neither feared to forgo his ſonne nor refuſed to kill him. Thou y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> canſt not be content, to forgo thy ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne by the lawe and lotte of mortalitie &amp; deathe, what woldeſt thou do, if thou war co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to kill thy ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne? The feare of God &amp; faithe ought to make the redye to al thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges. Be it that thou haſt loſt thy goodes, be it that par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of thy body ar co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually and gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly vexed with deadly diſeaſes, be it that thy wiffe, thy children &amp; deare
<pb facs="tcp:11414:8"/>frendes ar moſt dolefully and heaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pluct from the by deathe, lette not theſe thinges be ſtumbling blockes vnto the, but batailes: neither let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> weaken or ouerthrowe the faithe of a chriſtian, but let them rather declare ſtrenght in the wraſtling: Foraſmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che as all ſuffering of theſe preſent euelles ought to be diſpiſed in hope of the good thinges to come. Except ther ſhall furſt be a battayle, ther can be no victory, but whan a man in the ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the battaile getteth the victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, than is ther a crowne alſo geuen to them that ouercom: For in a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt the gouernour of a ſhipe is know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>en, &amp; a ſowdear is tried in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> battaile. The bragge is but wanton, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ther is no daunger: The conflicte and fight in aduerſite is the triall of the truthe. The tre that is depely roted is not mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued with the bluſtering windes: and a ſhippe that hathe ſtrong ribbes wel ioyned, is beaten of the wawes and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceaued no leake, and wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the corne is threſſed on to barne ſtore, the good &amp; weghty corne regardeth not the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, but the light chaffe ar blowen quite awaie. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thus thapoſtle Paule after ſhipwracke, after ſcorges, after
<pb facs="tcp:11414:8"/>many &amp; bitter tormentes of the fleſhe and the body, he ſayeth not that he is greued with theſe aduerſities but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended: ſo that the more greuouſly he is afficted, the more truly he is tried: Ther is geuen me (ſayeth he) the prick of my fleſhe,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.</note> the meſſenger of Satan that dothe buffet me, that I ſhould not be exalted: For the which I haue beſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the Lord .iii. tymes that it might departe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me: and he ſayd vnto me, my grace is ſufficient for thee, for po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer thorowe weakenes is made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite. Whan therfore either ſicknes, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther weaknes, or any deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dothe viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly aſſaile vs, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is our ſtrengt made perfect, than is faithe crowned, yf ſhe indure ſtedfaſte in temptacion:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccle.</hi> 27.</note> according as it is written: The fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nace trieth the potters veſſell, and the temptacion of troble trieth iuſte men. Furthermore this difference is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene vs and other that knowe not God: They complayne and grudge in their trobles: but as for vs, aduerſities do not call vs awaye from the truthe, vertue, and faythe, but do ſtrenghten vs in ſorowes. For wher as nowe the bloody flixe dothe ſcrape the guttes, &amp; taketh quite awaye the ſtrenght of the
<pb facs="tcp:11414:9"/>body, wheras nowe a fire inwardly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceaued in wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des &amp; ſores doth rage &amp; burne, wheras now the intralles do ſhake &amp; pant with continuall vomite, wheras the eyes are ſet on fire w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the violence of blood, wheras ſome mens fete or other ꝑtes of the body ar cut of that they ſhould not corrupte the reſt, wheras thorow damages &amp; hurtes of the body (after the diſeaſe once burſte out) either the goyng is weakened, or the hearing ſtopped, or the ſight blin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, al &amp; euery of thoſe profiteth vnto the inſtruction &amp; teaching of fayth. To fight againſt ſo many viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t aſſaultes of deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; death w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſtable mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, what a noble courage is it? &amp; how wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy auaunceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is it for a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de right vp, among the myſeries &amp; deſtru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctions of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kinde, &amp; not to lye groue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on thearth with them that haue no hope in the Lord? We ought rather to reioyce, and embrace the gyft of ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiles we ſtedfaſtly declare our faythe, and by ſuffering of paynes go by the narowe waye of Chriſt vnto Chriſt, we may (he bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g iudge) receiue the rewarde of lyfe &amp; faythe. Let hym feare to die: but he which being not re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>newed of the water &amp; the ſpirite, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuered
<pb facs="tcp:11414:9"/>in bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage to hel fire. Let him feare to dye,<note place="margin">who be they that feare dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the.</note> which is not inrolled in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> croſſe &amp; paſſion of Chriſt: Let him fear to die, which fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this death ſhall paſſe to the ſeconde deathe: let him feare to dye, whome after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> departure fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this worlde, an euerlaſting flame ſhal tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual puniſheme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: let him fear to dye, which by his long carieng here haue only this benefite, that his ſorowe &amp; torment is for the while dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred. Many of our brethren dye in this mortalitie, that is to ſay, many of our brethren are delyuered from this world. As this mortalitie is a peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to the Iewes &amp; gentiles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are Chriſtes enemies, euen ſo to goddes ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes it is an holſome departure. Where as without difference of mankinde y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſt die w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thoniuſte, ye maye not thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> both good &amp; euel are deſtroyed alyke.</p>
            <p>The iuſte are called he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to refreſhing, thoniuſte are caught awaye to puniſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment: Defence is quickly geuen to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that beleue: but to tho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>beleuers paine. We are moſte dearely beloued bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren vncircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpecte, and vnthankful to Goddes benefites, neither do we knowe what is geuen vnto vs. The virgins being in ſafetie, lo depte he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
<pb facs="tcp:11414:10"/>in peace with their glory, fearing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing the threateninges, deflowrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges &amp; brothel houſes of Antichriſt now co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming. The childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſcape the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of their ſlippery age, &amp; do luckely attayne the rewarde of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency. The tender matrone feareth now no more tormentes, which tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe a ſwift deathe is eſcaped y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of perſecutyon, and the handes and tormentes of the hang man. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe thextreme feare of mortalitie &amp; tyme, the luke warme are made hote, the diſſolute are hard wrongen, the ſlothefull ar reiſed vp, the ſhrinkers are compelled to returne, the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are conſtrained to beleue, the true faithfull people are called to reſt, and a newe &amp; a great arinye ys gathered together with a mightier force to the battayle, to fight when the filde ſhall beginne without any feare of deathe, which in the tyme of mortalitie came in to the warfare. Furthermore what thing ys this moſt dearely beloued brethren, how muche apperteining to the purpoſe, how neceſſary, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilence &amp; morren, which ſemeth to be horrible &amp; cruel dothe trie the rightful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes of euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; examineth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> myn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:11414:10"/>of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynde, whether the hole do ſeruice vnto the ſicke? whether neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boures &amp; kinſfolke do godly loue toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther? whether the maſters haue any pitie vpon their ſicke ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the phiſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s forſake the ſicke that hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly requireth their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel? whether the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ruel wil ceaſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ny &amp; wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge doyng? whether thextorcioners (at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt wyſe for feare of deathe) will quenche their inſaciable &amp; continuall burning of raging couetouſnes? whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proud wil ſtoupe &amp; bow downe their neckes? whether the wicked wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate his folehardines? whether the riche (wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their deare frendes are dead) wil yet tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geue to the poore, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelues ſhal dye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out heire? Certeinly althoughe this mortalitie ſhal bring with it none other profite, yet in this point it hathe muche profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted chriſtians &amp; goddes ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we beginne now gladly to wiſhe for martirdom, whiles we learne not to feare death. Vnto vs theſe are no buriales but execiſes. They geue a glorious ſtrengtht vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mynde, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the contempt of deathe they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare to the crowne. But paradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture ſome man maye obiecte &amp; ſaye: This
<pb facs="tcp:11414:11"/>tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this preſent mortalitie maketh me heauy, that where as I was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to confeſſe the fayth, &amp; had with my hole harte &amp; full ſtreinght addicte my ſelfe to ſuffre paſſion, I am nowe being preuented with death, depriued of my martirdome. For anſwere to this, we muſt firſt conſider, that mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirdome ſtandeth not in our power, but in theſtimacion of God, neither canſt thou ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſt loſt ought, which knoweſt not whether thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt deſerue to receyue. Beſides this, God which is the ſearcher of the rey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and harte, and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beholder &amp; kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of theyes ſeeth the, prayſeth and alloweth the, and he that perceyueth the to be prepared to vertue, will for vertue re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der rewarde. Had Cain now killed his brother whan he offered ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to God? and neuer theles God that forſeeth thinges old beforehande conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> murthering of his brother, which he had conceyued in his minde. As ther the wicked thought &amp; miſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceit was manifeſt vnto God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> forſeeth thinges: eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo among the ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God, which thinke to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe the truthe, &amp; are ful purpoſed to ſuffer martirdome, the mynde bent to good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (God being iudge) is crowned.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11414:11"/>
            <p>For it is one thing to wante a will to martirdome, &amp; on other to wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirdome to a ready wil. Loke what ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner of one God fyndeth thee when he talleth thee hence, ſuche a one dothe he alſo iudge thee, according as him ſelfe witneſſeth ſaing: &amp; al co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhal knowe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I am y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſearcher of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reynes &amp; of the harte. For God ſeketh not the effuſion of your blood, but faith. For neither wer Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I ſaat, nor Iacod ſlayne, and yet thorowe the merites of faith and rightfulnes they were hono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable, &amp; obteyned to be chief amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Patriarkes. Vnto whoſe feaſt all that are fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de faithfull, iuſte, &amp; prayſe wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy are gathered together. We ought to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that we ſhould do the wyll of God &amp; not our owne, according as God hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vs daily to pray. How arſewarde &amp; peuiſhe a mater is it for vs to deſire the will of God to be done, Seing we do not immediatly o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God his will, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he calleth vs out of this world? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this we ſtriue &amp; wreſtle, &amp; ar w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> heumes &amp; ſorow after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner of ſtub burne ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes brought vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lordes preſence, departing hence co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled by neceſſitie, &amp; not by willing obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: &amp; wil we w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly rewardes be hono<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red
<pb facs="tcp:11414:12"/>of him, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we com vnwilling<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly? For what purpoſe than do we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire &amp; praye for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of the king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome of heauen, yf we haue our delec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion in earthy captiuitie? why do we praye &amp; beſeche w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> often repeted prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that the day of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome might come quickly, yf our deſires be grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; earneſter to ſerue the deuil here, than to reigne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt ther? Further that the tokens of goddes prouidence maye more manifeſtly appere, that the Lorde (which knoweth aforehand thinges to cum) doeth prouide for the true healthe of his, when a certeine companion in office and felowe prieſt with vs being now wearied with ſick<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and trobled with deathe euen at hand, deſired a ſauecondute to be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, ther ſtode by him as he praied and being now at deathes dore, a yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g man in honour and maieſty worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, of ſtature tall, of countenaunce ſo cleare and bright, that the carnall eye of man could ſcante abide to behold ſuche a one ſtanding by him, but only becauſe he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhould go out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde might now abide to loke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch a one. And he not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> oute a certeyne an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre of minde and voice groned &amp; ſaid: you are afraid to ſuffer, departe hence
<pb facs="tcp:11414:12"/>ye will not, what ſhall I do to you? this ys a voice of one rebuking and warning, who will not conſent to the preſent deſire of ſuche as be carefull for perſecucyon, and careles for their calling hence, but referreth the hole matter vnto the tyme to come.</p>
            <p>Our brother and felowe in office heard that which he might declare to other. For he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> was now redy to die, hearde theſe wordes to that ende y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he might tel them to others, he heard the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not for himſelf but for vs. For what ſhould he learne being now ready to departe? He lerned ſomwhat, but that was for vs that here remayned, that whiles we parceaue that the prieſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deſired ſaueconducte was rebuked, we might knowe what was expedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for euery one of vs. How often hath it ben alſo reueled vnto vs that are the leſt &amp; out caſtes? How often hath God vouchſaued manifeſtly to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde vs, that we ſhould dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly witneſſe &amp; ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly preach, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we ought not to mour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne for our brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>. Lordes calling are deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the world? foraſmuche as I knowe, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they ar not loſt but ſent before, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they departing hence go before vs, &amp; ought to be wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for as men y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> are gone furth on a
<pb facs="tcp:11414:13"/>torney or ſailing, and not to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented: neither that we here ſhould put on black gownes,<note place="margin">Morning for the deade in blacke gownes.</note> ſeing they haue receiued ther white garmentes, that we ſhould giue non occaſion to the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiles that they might worthely &amp; iuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rebuke vs becauſe we mourne for them, as thoughe they wer deſtroyed and loſt, which we ſaie doo liue with God, and ſhould with the witneſſe of our harte and conſcience reproue that faithe which we profeſſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our mouth and doice. We ar tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſours of our hope and faithe, the thinges that we ſpeake ſeme to be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfaite, fayned, paited. yt profiteth nothing to profeſſe vertue in wordes, &amp; to deſtroy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth in dedes. Thapoſtle paule alſo doth re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>buke and blame ſuche as are ſorowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the departing of their frendes.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.</note> We will not (ſaieth he) haue you to be ignozau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> touching them that are aflepe, that you ſhould not be ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowefull as ſuche that haue no hope. For if we beleue that Ieſus died &amp; roſe againe, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo God ſhall alſo brig with him the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that haue ſlept in Chriſt. He ſaieth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they are ſorowefull in the departi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of theirs that haue no hope. But we which liue in hope, &amp; beleue
<pb facs="tcp:11414:13"/>in God, &amp; truſte in Chriſt that ſuffred for vs and roſe againe, abiding in Chriſt, &amp; thorowe him riſing againe in him, why do we our ſelues either re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſe to departe he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or mourne &amp; ſoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we for our fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des departing hence as thoughe they wer loſt? Seing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt him ſelfe the Lord and our God doeth warne vs ſaieng: I am y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he that beleueth in me althoughe he die, yet he ſhall liue:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> &amp; euery on that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth &amp; beleueth in me ſhall not die for euer. yf we beleue in Chriſt let vs geue credite to his wordes &amp; promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and we ſhal not die euerlaſtingly, but we ſhall come to Chriſt with a ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſafety, with whome we ſhall liue &amp; reigne alwaies. But wher as in the meane tyme we die, we doo but paſſe by deathe vnto immortalitie, neither can a man attayne eternal life, except he happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to go out from he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: it is no end but a paſſage, &amp; after this te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral iorney is finiſhed, a going ouer vnto euerlaſting lyfe. Who wil not make haſt to go to better thinges? Who wil not deſire to be chaunged and faſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a newe after thymage of Chriſt, &amp; to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpedely vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dignite of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly grace? accordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as Paule thapoſtle
<pb facs="tcp:11414:14"/>preached ſafeng, our conuerſacion is in heauen, from whence we alſo loke for the Lord Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Phi.</hi> 3.</note> which ſhall tranſforme our vile bodye, &amp; make it like vnto his gloriouſe body. The Lorde Chriſt alſo him ſelfe doeth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that we ſhall be ſuch, whan he praieth the father that we maye be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, and liue with him in theuerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſeates; and reioyce in the celeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all kingdomes: father (ſaith he) I wil that where I ſhall be thoſe whiche thou haſt geuen me maye be with me alſo,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 17.</note> and maye ſee the glory which thou haſt geuen me before the worlde was made. He that ſhall com to the ſeate of Chriſt, and to the glory of the heauenly kingdomes, ought neither to mourne nor tament, but rather according to the Lordes promiſe and the beleaue of the truthe, to reioyce in his tranſlation and ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. Thus do we finde that Enoch which pleaſed God, was tranſlated. For thus in the boke of Geneſis God<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des worde teſtifieth and ſaieth. And Enoch pleaſed God, and was not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwardes founde, bicauſe God had tranſlated him. This was the reward of pleaſing God, to obteyne to be cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:11414:14"/>out from the infectyon of this worlde. This the holy Gooſt teacheth alſo by Salomon, that they which pleaſe God ar plucked quickly hence &amp; ſpedily deliuered,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sapi.</hi> 4.</note> leaſt that they ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rieng long in this worlde, might be defiled with the handelinges of the ſame: He was caught awaie (ſaithe he) leſt thorowe malice his vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding ſhould chaunge. For his ſowle pleaſed the Lord<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> therfore he made haſt to bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g him out from the myddes of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: Thus the ſowle it ſelf being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicte vnto God, maketh haſt in the pſalmes alſo vnto the Lord thorowe ſpiritual faith, as it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83.</note> O Lord of hoſtes how louing at thy dwelling places, my ſowle deſireth and maketh haſt vnto the courtes of God. yf is his parte to deſire to dwelle long in the worlde, whoſe delectacion is in the worlde, whome the flattering and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful worlde doth allure w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> enticeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of earthy pleaſures. Furthermore foraſmuche as the world hateth the chriſtian, why loueſt thou him that hateth the, and doeſt not rather folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we Chriſt, which hathe redemed the, and loueth the? Iohn in his epiſtle crieth, ſpeaketh and exhorteth, that
<pb facs="tcp:11414:15"/>we ſhuld not (folowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g carnal deſires) loue the world,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 2.</note> ſaieng: loue not the world, neither the thinges that ar in the world. Yf any man ſhall loue the worlde, the charitie of the father is not in him, bicauſe all that is in the world, is the luſt of the fleſhe, the luſt of theyes, &amp; the pride of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, which is not of the father, but of the luſt of the world, and the worlde ſhall paſſe awaye with his luſt: but he that ſhall do the wil of God, ſhall abide for euer, euen as God abideth for euer. Furthermore let vs moſt dearely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued brethren be ready with a ꝑfecte mynde, a ſtedfaſt faithe, &amp; ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g power to obey all the will of God: let vs ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhe the feare of deathe, and thinke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> immortalitie that foloweth. Let vs ſhewe our ſelues to be that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we beleaue: So that we neither mourne for the departure of our deare fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, and whan the daie ſhall come of our owne calling hence, we may without delaye and gladly go at the Lordes call. This thing foraſmuche as it ſhould be done of Goddes ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes alwaies, muche more at this preſent it ought to be obſerued, Seing the world is now in decayeing, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeged
<pb facs="tcp:11414:15"/>with the blonſteri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſtes of deadly euilles: that we which doo ſee greuous thinges to be already be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, and knowe that more greuous hang ouer our heades, ſhould counte it the greateſt gaine if we maye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parte hence quickly. Yf the walles of thine houſe were ſo olde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhoke, and the roofe ouer the did tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble, the houſe being now weried, being now tired, &amp; the buildinges falling downe for age, did threate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an ouerthrowe to be at hande, woldeſt thou not with all ſpede get thee out? Yf a trobleſome &amp; ſtormye te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſt, and the waues being lift vp with a violent winde, did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forehande ſhewe the a ſhippewracke comming, woldeſt thou not ſaile in to ſome hauen with out delaye? Beholde the worlde ſhaketh and decaieth, and doeth declare her owne downe falle, not now with the age, but with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of thinges: and doeſt not thou giue thankes to God; and reioyce on thine owne behalfe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou art quickely take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence and deliuered from the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, ſhippewrackes &amp; plages that are houeri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ouer vs? We ought to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidre moſt derely beloued brethren, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten tymes to thinke, that we haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken
<pb facs="tcp:11414:16"/>the worlde, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we liue here but for a tyme as ſtraungers and pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. Let vs embraſe that daye which may appoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te euery one of vs his dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ling place, which doeth reſtore vs to paradiſe and to the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, after that we ar taken hence, and deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſnares of the world: Who being farre out of his owne cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trey, maketh not haſte to returne home? Who making haſte to ſayle to his frendes and kinſfolke, wolde not earneſtly deſire a proſperous winde, that he might the rather imbrace his dearely beloued? We reken that para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe is our countre, we beginne now to haue the patriarches for our paren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, why do we not make haſt &amp; ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, that we maye ſe our countrey, hat we maye ſalute our parentes? A great number of our parentes, brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſonnes do ther abide vs, a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany do wiſhe for vs, which are now ſure of their owne immortalitie, and carefull for our ſafetye. To come to the ſight and imbraſing of theſe, how great ioye ſhall it be bothe to vs and them? what maner of pleaſure is this of the heauenly kingdomes, to be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feare of dieing and to lyue with
<pb facs="tcp:11414:16"/>euerlaſtyngnes? How excellent and perpetuall happines is this? Ther is the glorious co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of the Apoſtles: Ther are the numbre of the reioyſing prophetes. Ther are an infinite com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panye of martyrs, that are crowned for the victory of their fight and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. The triumphing virgins are there, which thorow the ſtrenght of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinency, haue ſubdued the luſte of the fleſhe and bodye: Ther are the mercy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full rewarded, which haue done the workes of ryghtfulneſſe, by geuyng almes, &amp; fedyng the poore: which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing the Lordes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes, haue chaunged their earthly patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies for heauenly treaſures. Let vs moſt dearly beloued brethren w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire make haſte vnto theſe, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> vs wiſhe that we maye quickely be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them, that it maye be our fortune ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dely to come to Chriſt. Let God ſe this cogitacion and thought of oures, let the Lorde Chriſt beholde this purpoſe of our mynde and faythe, which ſhall gyue the greater rewardes of his glory to them, whoſe deſyres are more earneſt to be with him. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11414:17"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A boke of the holy</hi> martir G. Chpriane, conicining an exhortation to martyrdome, diuided into, xii. chapters, wherin the ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me of the hole mater is more fully knowen. written vnto Fortunatus.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuche as O moſt deare Fortunatus the heuy burden of trobles and perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s do lye vpon the churche, &amp; nowe in thende of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſe tyme of Antichriſt beginneth to approche, thou haſt deſired me to prepare &amp; ſtrenghte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mindes of the brethren with exhortacions of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcriptures, wherby Chriſtes ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers myght be encorraged vnto the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritual &amp; heauenly fight. It behoued me to obey this thy moſt neceſſary de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, that (to the vttermoſt of our lytle power, by the helpe of goddes inſpira<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion) we might bring furth out of god<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des worde, as it were certeine armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res and defences for the brethren that ſhall fight. For it is but a ſmale mater for vs, to raiſe vp goddes people with
<pb facs="tcp:11414:17"/>the trompe of our voice, excepte we ſtrenghten by the holy ſcriptures the faithe of ſuche as beleue, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoute vertue that is conſecrate vnto God. For what thing agreeth better and more with our paſtorall cure and charge, then to prepare and furniſhe the people committed vnto vs of God, and the armey ſtanding in the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tentes, againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> arrowes and dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of the deuell? For he can not be a mete ſouldear for the battaile, which haue not ben before exerciſed in the felde. Or who ſeking a victorious crowne ſhall in the courſe or ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng place be crowned, except beforehande he do conſyder the experience of his ſtrenght and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyng? The aduerſary &amp; enemy with whom we fight, is aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient &amp; of long experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. For ſix thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande yeres are fully complete, ſence the deuel began to fight againſt man. Therfore he hath now learned eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cient exerciſe, al kindes of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, al ſottelties &amp; deceytes to caſt vs dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. Yf he ſhal fynde Chriſtes ſouldear vnprepared, yf he ſhal fynd him ygno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, negligent, &amp; not diligently wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching: he encloſeth in the ignoraunt,
<pb facs="tcp:11414:18"/>he deceaueth the negligent, he begy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the foliſhe. But yf any man kea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Lordes commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dementes, and ſtycking manfully vnto Chriſt, ſhall ſtand vp againſt him: he muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des be ouercom, bicauſe Chriſt whom man confeſſeth is inuincible. But to make a ſhorte tale, leſt with long wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting I ſhould wery y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt deare bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being occupied either in hearing or in reading, I haue knit vp the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in a fewe wordes, that vnto the tit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les that at ſet abrode (which euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ought bothe to knowe and reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber) I might adde the Lordes wordes, &amp; by authorire of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuine ſcriptures co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which I had ſet before mens eies: ſo that I maye not ſo muche ſeame to haue ſent vnto the this trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of myne owne writig, as to haue geuen occaſion to other to write trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſis: which thing being vſed of eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, is profitable for many. For if I ſhould now geue vnto the a garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ready made, the garment ſhould be myne, which an other ſhould we are, &amp; paraduenture a thing made for an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wold not ſerue for the proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſtature of his body. But now I haue ſent vnto the the ſelfe wolle and
<pb facs="tcp:11414:18"/>purple of the lanibe, by whom we are redempre &amp; made aliue, which whan thou haſt rereaued, thou ſhalt make for thy ſelfe a coate at thine owne plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, wherin thou ſhalt more reioyce, than in thy accuſtomed and proper garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes: and thou ſhalt deliuer this that we haue ſent vnto others, that they maye alſo according to their owne will make for them ſelues gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, that al men (the old nakednes being couered) maye put on the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of Chriſt, being clothed word we the ſanctificacion of the heauenly grace. Furthermore in this moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarye exhortacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which maye ſtire vp men to ſuffer martyrdome, I haue perceaued this cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel alſo moſt deare brother to be bothe profitable &amp; hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, to cut of the lettes and hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunces of our owne wordes, and to take awaye the goinges about the buſhe of mans talke: and to allege ſuche thynges only as God him ſelfe ſpeaketh, wherby Chriſt prouoketh his ſeruautes to martyrdome. For the ſelfe commaundemeetes of the Lord as armors and weapons ought to be put in to the myndes of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fight.
<pb facs="tcp:11414:19"/>Let them be the exhortacions of the warlike trompet, let them be the peale of trompettes that maye prouoke to fyght. Thorowe them let the eares be lifte vp, thorowe them let the mindes be inſtructed &amp; taught, thorowe them let the ſtrenght boche of the mynde &amp; body be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed, to ſuffer all maner of afflictions and tormentes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let vs (which by the ſufferau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God haue geuen the firſt baptiſme vn to them that beleue) prepare euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to another baptiſme alſo, putting them in mynde and teaching, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this baptiſme is in grace greater, in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer myghtier, in honour more preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: a baptiſme wherin Angels bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, and wherin God and his Chriſt reioyſe: a baptiſme after the receyte wherof no man ſynneth any more: a baptiſme that maketh perfecte the encreaſe of our fayth, a baptiſme that do immediatly couple vs vnto God, when we departe this worlde.</p>
            <p>In the baptiſme of water is receyued the remiſſion of ſynnes, in the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of blood the crowne of vertues. This thing ought to be embraſed and wyſhed for, and to be deſyred by the ſeruent prayers of vs all, that we
<pb facs="tcp:11414:19"/>which are the ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of God, may be alſo his frendes.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>The firſt Chapter.</head>
               <p>In exhorting therfore &amp; preparing our brethren,<note place="margin">The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentes of the. <hi>12.</hi> chapters.</note> thorowe the ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe of faythe &amp; vertue, to attayne the glorye of confeſſing the Lorde, and to arme them to the bataile of perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and ſuffering, we muſt firſt of al declare, that the ydolles which ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mateth for himſelfe are no goddes for the thinges that are made, are not grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than their mater: neither can theſe ydolles defende and ſaue any man, which wolde them ſelues peryſhe from their temples, except they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of man. Neither ought thelementes to be worſhipped, which according to thordenaunce and commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement of God do ſerue man.</p>
               <p>The ydolles being ouerthrowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and the maner of the lemonies declared,<note place="margin">The. <hi>2.</hi> chap.</note> we muſt ſhewe that the Lorde onlye ought to be worſhipped.</p>
               <p>To theſe then muſt we adde, what is the threatning of God againſt them, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> that do ſacrifice to ydolles.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11414:20"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> We muſt teache furthermore that God wil not eaſely pardon Idolarers.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> And that God is ſo greued with I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie, that he hathe alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded them to be ſlayne, which haue en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yſed men to ſacrifice and ſerue ydolles.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> To theſe muſte be added, that the whiche are redemed and made aly<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e thorow the blood of Chriſt, ought to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e ferre nothing before Chriſt: becauſe he preſerred nothing before vs, but for our ſales he preferred aduerſitie before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie, pouertie before ryches, bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage, before lordſhip, death before immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarywyſe we in our ſufferinges preferre the ryches and pleaſures of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe before worldlye pouertie, the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and euerlaſting kingdome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore temporall bondage, immortalitie before deathe, God and Chriſt before the deuell and Antichriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> We ought alſo to bring to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce that none that are eſcaped out of the deuelles clouches, and delyuered from the ſnares of the worlde, ſhoulde deſire (yf they happen to fall into afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions and troubles) to go forthe againe vnto the worlde, and ſo loſe that they had eſcaped.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> But rather that they ought to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure
<pb facs="tcp:11414:20"/>&amp; continue in faythe, inthe truthe, and in the perfectyon of the heuenly, and ſpirituall grace, that they maye ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne the victory and crowne.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> We muſt alſo ſhewe that afflictions and perſecutions doo therfore happen that we maye be tryed:</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> And that the ſufferinges of wronge and batailes of perſecution ought not to be feared: becauſe the Loide is more myghty to defende, than the deuel is to fight againſt vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> And to the intent no man ſhould be afrayde and trobled thorowe afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and perſecutions which we ſuffer in this worlde, we muſt proue that it was toloe beforeha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, that the worlde ſhould hate vs, and that it ſhould ſtire vp per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutions againſt vs, that the truthe of Goddes promiſe in rewardes that ſhal hereafter folowe, myght manifeſtly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by this ſelf thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in that theſe per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecutions do happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Neither dothe any newe thing happen nowe vnto chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, for aſmuche as good me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the beginning of the world haue ben perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted, &amp; the rightful haue ben oppreſſed and Filled of the vnrightfull.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> Laſt of all we muſt declare, what hope and what rewarde abydeth the
<pb facs="tcp:11414:21"/>rightfull men and martyrs after the af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>flictions and paſſyons of this liffe, and that we ſhall receiue more in rewarde of our ſuffering, than we ſuffer here in the ſelf afflictyons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>The firſt chapter.</head>
               <p>THat ydolles are no goddes, and that none of theleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ſhould he worſhipped in goddes ſtede is manifeſt in the .Cxiij. pſalme. The ydol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles ar gold &amp; ſiluer,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes of mens handes. Mowthes haue they, but they ſpeake not, they haue eyes and ſee not. They haue eares &amp; heare not, neither is ther any breath in theyr mowthe. Let them be like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that make them. In likema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in the boke of the wiſdome of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamon it is writen:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sap.</hi> 15.</note> They haue eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as Goddes all thidolles of the na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions, which haue neither eyes to ſee, neither noſtrels to drawe brethe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eares to heare, nor fingars on theyr handes to feale: Their fete alſo are vnhapte and ſloo to walke. For man made them, and he that hathe a borowed ſpirite faſhtoned them. But no man can make a God like vnto him ſelfe: For Seing he ys mortal, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11414:21"/>is alſo but a deade thing, which he fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhioneth with vngodlye handes: For he that maketh them, is more excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t than y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinges which he worſhippeth.</p>
               <p>We reade alſo in the boke of Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> Thou ſhall not make for thy ſelfe any grauen ymage, neither the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of any thing. Further as touchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thelementes Salamon ſaith: Neither toke they ſo muche regarde of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes that ar made,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sapi.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> as to knowe who was the crafteſman of them: but ſome toke the fire, ſome the aire, ſome the winde, ſome the courſe of the ſtarres, ſome the great water, ſome the Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne &amp; Mone for goddes. But thoughe they had ſuche pleaſure in their veauty, that they thought them to haue ben Goddes: yet ſholde they haue knowe, howe muche more fairer ys he that made them. Or yf they marueled at the power and workes of them, they might haue perceiued therby, that he that made theſe mighty thinges, is mightyer then they.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>The .ij. chapter.</head>
               <p>THat god only ought to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped we reade in Deuterono,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deu.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Exo.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> Thou ſhalt worſhippe thy Lord God and him only ſhalt thou ſerue. Alſo in Exo
<pb facs="tcp:11414:22"/>dus. Thou ſhalt haue non other gods beſides me. In like maner in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame boke of Deuteronomy: Se now how y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I, I am he, and that ther is no God beſides me:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deu.</hi> 32.</note> I can kil and make aliue, I ſtrike and heale againe: neither is ther any, that can deliuer any man out of my handes.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apo.</hi> 14.</note> Iohan alſo in the reuelacion ſaithe: And I ſawo an Angel flie in the myddes of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, hauing an euerlſtaing goſpel to prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the vnto them that litte and dwelle on thearthe, and to all nacions, kinreds &amp; tonges and people, ſaing with a loude voice: Feare God rather, and giue ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to him, for the howre of his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement is com: and worſhippe him that made heauen and earthe, the ſed and all that in them ys. In like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner alſo the Lord maketh mentyon in the goſpell of the firſt and ſecond co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement ſaing: He are Iſrael, The Lord thy God ys one Lord: And thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God with all thy harte,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 22.</note> and with al thy ſowle, and with al thy ſtrenght. This ys the firſt commaundement: and the ſecond ys like vnto this, Thou ſhalt loue thy neyghboure as thy ſelfe. In theſe two co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundementes-conſiſteth the hoſt
<pb facs="tcp:11414:22"/>lawe &amp; ꝑphetes. And againe: This is eternall liffe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 17.</note> that they ſhould knowe the alone the true God, &amp; Ieſus Chriſt whome thou haſt ſent.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>The .iij. chapter.</head>
               <p>VVhat God threatneth to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> do ſacrifice to ydols, we maye reade in Exodus thus:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.</note> He y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offereth vnto any goddes ſaue to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord only ſhal be roted out. Alſo in the Deu teronomye.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deu.</hi> 32.</note> They offered vnto druels and not vnto God.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 2.</note> In like maner in Eſay: They worſhipped the Idolles which their owne fingars had made: Ther kneleth the man, ther falleth the man downe before them, ſo that thou canſt not bring him awaye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: And againe, To them you haue pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out your drinke offeringes, and to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you haue offered your ſacrifices: ſhal not I be angry w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges ſai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth the Lord? In like maner Hieremy ſaith: walke not after ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge goddes to ſerue them, &amp; worſhippe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hiere.</hi> 7.</note> nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther prouoke me thorowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes of your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des to ſcatter you abrode. Io. alſo in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reuelacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaithe:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apo.</hi> 14.</note> If any doo
<pb facs="tcp:11414:23"/>worſhippe the beſt and his ymage, &amp; ſhall receue his marke in his fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head or in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, he alſo ſhal drin ke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wine of Goddes wrathe myng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cuppe of his wrathe: &amp; he ſhal be puniſhed with fire &amp; brymſtone in the preſence of the holy angels, &amp; in the preſence of the lambe. And the ſmoke of their tormentes ſhal aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de vp euermore. Neither ſhal they haue any reſt daye or night, who ſo euer they be that ſhall worſhipe the beſt &amp; his ymage.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>The .iiij. chapter</head>
               <p>THat God wil not eaſely iꝑ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don ydolaters, it appeareth by Moſes in Exodus, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth for the people, and yet obteyned not: Oh Lorde (ſaithe he) this people haue ſynned a great ſynne,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.</note> and made for them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues Goddes of gold: yet forgeue them their ſinne I beſeche the: yf not, wipe me out of the boke which thou haſt write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And the Lord ſaid vnto Moſes? I will put him out of my boke, that hathe ſynned againſt me. In like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner whan Ieremy praied for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb facs="tcp:11414:23"/>the Lord ſpake vnto him ſaieng:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iere.</hi> 7.</note> Thou ſhalt not praie for this people, thou ſhalt neither geue thankes, nor byd praier for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for I wil not heare them in the tyme that they ſhall call vpon me, in the tyme of theyr troble.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezech.</hi> 14.</note> Ezechiell alſo threateneth the ſame wrathe of God againſt them, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſynne againſt God ſaieng: and the worde of the Lord came vnto me ſaieng: Thou ſonne of man, whan the land ſinneth againſt me, and goeth furthe in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes: I ſhall ſtretche out myne ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vpon it, and deſtroy all the prouiſion of their bread, and I will ſend hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger among them, to deſtroye man &amp; beſt in the land. And thoughe Noah, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel, &amp; Iob theſe .iii. me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> war amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet ſhall they deliuer neither ſonnes nor daughters but ſhall them ſelues only be ſaffe. In likemaner in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> furſt boke of kings it is write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: yf one man ſynne agaiſt an other,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 2.</note> they ſhal make interceſſion vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord for him, but if a man ſynne againſt the Lord, who ſhall praie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for him?</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>The .v. chapter.</head>
               <p>THat God is ſoangrey w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ydolatry, that he hathe alſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be ſlayne which haue entiſed
<pb facs="tcp:11414:24"/>others to offer to ydolles and to ſerue them we reade in the Deuteronomy:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deu.</hi> 13.</note> Yf thy brother, or thyne owne ſonne, or thy daughter or thy wiffe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lieth in thy boſome, or thy frende which is as thine owne ſowle vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> entiſe the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly ſaie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, let vs go &amp; ſerue ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge goddes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goddes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles: y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent vnto him, nor herken vnto him, neither ſhal thine eye ſpare him, nor kepe him ſecrete, but ſhalt vtter him. Thine hande ſhall be firſt vpon him to kill him, and than the handes of all the people. To be ſhort they ſhal ſtone him and he ſhall dye, becauſe he went about to turne thee awaye fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde thy God. And agayne the Lord ſpeaketh and ſayeth, that a cytie ought not to be ſpared, althou the hole tytie ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent to Idolatrie: Yf thou ſhalt heare ſaye (of one of thy cyties which the Lorde thy God ſhall geue thee to dwel in) that they ſaye: Let vs go and ſerue ſtraunge Goddes, whiche thou haſte not knowen: Thou ſhalt ſmyte &amp; kill with thedge of the ſworde all that are in that cytie, and thou ſhalt burne the cytie w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fire, &amp; it ſhall neuer more be inhabited: Yea it ſhall neuer be buylt againe, that God may turne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11414:24"/>his fearce wrathe. And the Lorde ſhal ſhewe the mercy, and haue compaſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> on the, and multiply the, yf thou ſhalt heare the voice of the Lorde thy God, and keape his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de mentes. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thathias beyng myndfull of the force of this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement ſlewe him that came to thaltar to do ſacrifice.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Mac.</hi> 2.</note> But yf before the comming of Chriſt theſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes touching the worſhipi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of God, and deſpiſing of ydolles, war obſcrued &amp; keapt: How muche more ought they to be keapt after the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Chriſt? Foraſmuche as he at his comming did not exhorte vs with wordes only, but alſo with deades: which after he had ſuffred al maner of iniure is and reuiling wordes, was alſo crucified, to teache vs by his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, bothe to ſuffer and die: that who ſo euer he be that will not ſuffer for his ſake, ſhould be vtterly w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cuſe, foraſmuche as he hathe ſuffred for vs. And ſeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he hathe ſuffred for other mens ſynnes, muche more ought euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſuffer for his owne ſynnes. And therfore in the goſpel he treatneth and ſaithe: who ſo euer ſhal confeſſe me before men,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 10.</note> him wil I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo confeſſe before my father which is
<pb facs="tcp:11414:25"/>in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but who ſo euer ſhall denye me before men, him wil I alſo denye before my father which is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. In like maner thapoſtle paule ſaithe: Yf we die together with him we ſhall alſo liue together with him:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</note> Yf we ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with him we ſhall alſo raygne to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether with him: Yf we denye him he ſhall alſo denye vs. Iohan alſo ſaieth:<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 2.</note> he that denieth the ſonne hathe not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father, he that confeſſeth the ſonne, hathe bothe the ſonne and the father. Wherfore the Lord dothe exhorte and ſtrenghten vs to deſpiſe deathe:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 10.</note> ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng: Feare ye not them that kil the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy, but can not kill the ſowle: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feare him, which can kille bothe ſowle and body in to hell fire.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan.</hi> 12.</note> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine he ſaieth, he that loueth his life ſhall loſe it, and he that hateth his liffe in this worlde, ſhall preſerue it vnto eternal liffe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>The .vi. chapter.</head>
               <p>THat we which ar rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte &amp; made aliue thorowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blode of Chriſt, ought to preferre no thing before Chriſt, the Lord ſpeaketh in the goſpel and ſaithe: he that loueth father or
<pb facs="tcp:11414:25"/>mother aboue me, is not worthy of me.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 10.</note> And he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> taketh not vp his croſſe &amp; folowe me, is not worthy of me. In y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Deuteronomy it is alſo write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in like maner:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deu.</hi> 33.</note> They that ſaie to father or mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther I knowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> not, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> parents y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue not knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their owne ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, theſe haue keapt thy commaundementes, and obſerued thy teſtament.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> In like maner ſaieth thapoſtle Paule: Who ſhall ſeparate vs from the charite of Chriſt? ſhall tribulacion, or anguiſhe, either perſecution or hungar, either nakednes, or daunger, or the ſword? as it is writen: For thy ſake are we killed al the daie long,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 43</note> and are cown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as ſhepe appointed to be ſlayne. Neuertheles in all theſe thinges we ouercome, thorowe his helpe that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs. And againe he ſaithe: ye are not your owne, for ye are bought with a great price.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> Therfore glorifie and beare god in your body. And againe: he died for all that they which liue, ſhould not now liue to them ſelues,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</note> but to him which died for them, and roſe againe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>The .vij. chapter.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:11414:26"/>
               <p>THat they which are plucte out of the deuelles Iawes, and deliuered from the ſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of the world, ought not to returne agayne to the worlde leſt they ſhould loſe that they war eſcaped, The people of the Iues before figured after the ſhadowe and image of vs, whan they hade eſcaped thorowe the healpe and deliueraunce of God the moſt cruel bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage of Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rao &amp; Egipte, that is to ſaye, of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell: They being vnfaithfull and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull to God, did murmur agaiſt Moſes: They co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering the dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gers of the wildernes and labor, and vnder ſtanding not Goddes benefites of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty and ſaluacion, ſought to retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne againe in to Egipte, that ys to the bondage of this world from which they were deliuered. Whan as they ought rather to haue truſted and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaued in God: bicauſe that he which hathe deliuerde his people from the deuell &amp; the world, ſhal defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are deliuered.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exo.</hi> 14.</note> Why haſt thou (ſayd they) ſerued vs thus, for to cary vs out of E<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gipte? it had ben better for vs to haue ſerued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Egiptyans, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to die in this wildernes. And Moſes ſaid vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple.
<pb facs="tcp:11414:26"/>Stande vp boldly, and behold the ſaluacion that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth from the Lord, which the lord wil do for vs this daie. The Lord him ſelfe ſhall fight for you, and you ſhall hold your peace. Of this thing the Lord doeth alſo in his goſpel warne vs &amp; teache vs, that we ſhould not returne againe to the deuel and the world whome we haue forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; from whome we haue eſcaped, ſaie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luce.</hi> 9. <hi>and.</hi> 17.</note> No man putting his hande to the ploughe and loking backe ys mete for the kingdome of God. And againe he ſaieth: he that is in the felde, let him not returne backe: Remember Lottes wiffe. And leſtany might be hindered in the folowing of Chriſt, either tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe any worldly luſt, or thorowe thaffectyon and loue to his kinſfolke and frendes, he added, and ſaieth: He that doeth not forſake al that he hathe can not be my diſciple.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>The .viij. chapter.</head>
               <p>VVe muſt endure &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue in faith &amp; vertue, &amp; in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ꝑfec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſpiritual grace, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we maye attayne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> victory &amp; crowne. In the .ij. boke of Cronicles we reade thus:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Pard.</hi> 15.</note> The Lord abbideth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you, as lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g as ye abide w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11414:27"/>him: but yf ye ſhal forſake him, he ſhal alſo forſake you. In like maner ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Ezechiei.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eze.</hi> 33.</note> In what ſo euer daye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rightouſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal wander oute of the waie, his rightfulnes ſhal not deliuer him.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 10. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 8.</note> The Lord alſo in the goſpel ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth &amp; ſaieth: He that ſhall contynue to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the ſame ſhal be ſaffe: &amp; againe he ſaieth: if you ſhal abide in my wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de, ye ſhal verely be my diſciples, and ſhall knowe the truthe, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truthe ſhall make you fre. He alſo beforeha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning vs to be alwaies prepared, and to ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fully in a redynes, he added and ſaieth: Let your loynes be girte about,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 12.</note> and your lightes burning, and ye your ſelues like vnto men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> waite for their maſter, whan he wil returne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a wedding, that aſſone as he ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; knocke, they may ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him. Happye are thoſe ſeruauntes which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, ſhal finde wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. In likemaner y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed Apoſtle exhorteth vs to go forwarde &amp; encrea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe in faithe, vntil it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me to perfectyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaieng: knowe ye not that they which runne in a corſe, runne al, yet but one receiueth the crowne. So runne that ye maye obtayne.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.</note> And they do yt to ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne
<pb facs="tcp:11414:27"/>a corruptible crowne, but we to obtayne an incorruptible crowne. And againe he ſaieth, No man that warreth vnto God,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</note> entangleth him ſelfe with worldly cares: that he maye pleaſe him of whome he is allowed to be a ſowldier. And thoughe a man ſtriue for a maſtery, yet is he not crowned, except he ſtriue laufully. The ſame Apoſtle ſaithe alſo:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.</note> I beſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che you brethren by the merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God, that you make your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies a quicke ſacrifice, holy, and pleſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to God: and faſhion not your ſelues like vnto this world, but be ye chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in your ſhape, by the renewieng of your ſpirite, that ye maye proue, what thing that good, and pleaſing, &amp; perfecte will of God is. And againe he ſaieth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> We are the ſonnes of God: But and if we be ſonnes, we are alſo heires: the heyres I meane of God, and heires annexed with Chriſt: Yf ſo be that we ſuffer toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that we maye be glorified toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The exhortacion of the dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine preaching ſpeaketh the ſame thinges in the reuelacion ſaieng:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apo.</hi> 5.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11414:28"/>holdefaſt hat thou haſt, that another taketh not thy crowne. An enſample of this enduring and continuing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thende, is ſet forth in Exodus, wher as Moſes in the ſigne and ſacrament of the croſſe, lyfteth vp his heauy han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des to ouercome Amalech, which bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the figure of the deuell: Neither could he ouercome thaduerſary, vntyl he continued ſtable in the ſigne, with his handes continually lifted vp. And it happened (ſaieth he) that Iſrael had the better, when Moſes helde vp his hande:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 17.</note> And when he let his hande downe, Amalech had the better. And they toke a ſtone, &amp; put it vnder him, &amp; he ſat downe theron. And Aaron and Hur ſtayed vp his handes, the one on the one ſyde and the other on thother ſyde, and his handes were ſtedy vntyl y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sunne was downe. And Ieſus put Amalech to flight &amp; al his people. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde ſaid to Moſes: write this for a remembrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in a boke, and tel it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Ieſu. For I wil put out the remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>braucne of Amalech from vnder hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>The .ix. Chapter.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:11414:28"/>
               <p>THat troubles and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions do therfore happen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we maye be tried we reade in the Deuteronomy:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deu.</hi> 25.</note> The Lorde your God doth te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pte or proue you, that he may knowe whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you loue him w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your hole hert and with all your ſoule, and wyth all your ſtrenght. Againe it is written in Salomon: The furnace proueth the potters veſſell,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccle.</hi> 27.</note> and temtacion of troble trieth rightfull men. In lyke maner Paule teſtifieth and ſpeaketh the ſame, ſayeng: We reioyce in hope of the glory that ſhalbe geuen of God: Neyther do we ſo only,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.</note> but alſo we re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ioyce in trobles, knowing that tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacion bringeth pacience, but pacience bringeth triall, trial hope, and hope is not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, becauſe the loue God is ſpreade abrode in our hertes, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gooſt which is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs. Peter alſo in his epiſtle writeth and ſayeth: Dearely beloued maruell not at this heate that is come among you to trye you (that ye fall not awaye) as tho any newe thing ſhould happen vnto you:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.</note> but as ofte as ye are made partakers of Chriſtes paſſions, reioyce in al thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, that ye maye at thappearing of
<pb facs="tcp:11414:29"/>his glory reioyce with gladneſſe. Yf ye be rayled vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name of Chriſt, happye are ye: For the name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie &amp; power of God reſteth in you: the which name verely is blaſphemed of them, but by vs it is glorifyed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>The .x. Chapter.</head>
               <p>THat iniuries and the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of perſecution ought not to be feared, &amp; that no man ſhould be amaſed at troubles and perſecutions, which he ſuffereth in this worlde, for-becauſe the Lorde is more myghtye to defende, than the deuell is to fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs: Iohn in his epiſtell writeth and ſayeth:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 4.</note> He that is in you is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, than he that is in the worlde. In lyke maner in the pſalme: The Lorde is my helper, I wil not fear what ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can do vnto me. And agayne in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pſalme: Theſe boaſt them ſelues in their horſes, but we will boaſt our ſelues in the name of the Lorde our God.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 117. <hi>and.</hi> 19.</note> They are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de &amp; are falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, but we are ryſen &amp; ſtande vpright. And yet further the holy Gooſt (tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching and declaring that the armyes
<pb facs="tcp:11414:29"/>of the deuell ought not to be feared, al thoo he ſhoulde proclaime battaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, but rather that we ſhould haue our truſt in the ſelfe ſame battel, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ryghtfull by fighting againſt the deuell, may attayne to the reward of Goddes ſeate and eternal lyfe) ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth in the ſpalme &amp; ſayeth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.</note> Thoughe an hooſt of men were layde againſt me, yet ſhall not my harte be afrayed, and thoughe ther aroſe vp warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, yet wil I put my truſte in him. One thing haue I deſired of the Lord which I wil require, that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lorde all the dayes of my life. In lyke maner the holy ſcripture in Exodus doth declare that we do exceadingly multiplye and encreaſe thorowe afflictions and trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bles ſayeng:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.</note> And the more they oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed them, the more they multiplyed &amp; grewe. And in the Reuelacion god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des protection is promyſed vnto vs in our ſufferinges, where he ſayeth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apo.</hi> 2.</note> fear thou none of theſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges, which thou ſhalt ſuffre. Neither is it any other that promyſeth vnto vs ſaffetie &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, but euen very he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by the ꝓphet Eſay ſpeaketh &amp; ſayeth: Feare y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> not,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſaie.</hi> 41.</note>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11414:30"/>For I haue redemed the: I haue cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lee the by thy name, thou arte myne owne. And yf thou ſhalte go thorowe the water I am with the, and the flod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſhall not ouerwhelme the. And yf thou ſhalt paſſe thorowe the fire, the fire ſhall not burne the. For I am the Lorde thy God which do kepe thee in ſafetie. Which in the Goſpel alſo doth promiſe, that the helpe of God ſhall not faile goddes ſeruauntes in theyr perſecutions ſaieng:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 10.</note> but wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyuer you vp, take no thought how or what ye ſhall ſpeake. For it ſhalbe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you in that ſame houre, what ye ſhall ſaye. For it is not ye that ſpeake, but the ſpirite of your father that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth in you. And againe he ſayeth: put in your heartes not to ſtudye before, what ye ſhall anſwere:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 13. <hi>Luc.</hi> 21.</note> for I wil gyue you a mouthe &amp; wiſdome wher vnto your aduerſaries ar not able to reſiſt. Thus doeth God ſpeake alſo to moſes in exodus, which delaied to do his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement and feared the people, ſaieng:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Exo.</hi> 4.</note> Who hath made ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s mouth? or who hathe made the domme or the deafe, the ſeyng or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blynde, haue not I the Lorde God? Go nowe therfore, and I will open thy mouthe, &amp; I wyll
<pb facs="tcp:11414:30"/>teache the what thou ſhalt ſpeake.</p>
               <p>Neither is it any harde mater for God to open the godly mans mouth, and to enſpire conſtancy and holdnes of ſpeche vnto his confeſſor:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nu.</hi> 22.</note> which (as we reade in the boke of Numbres) did make the very Aſſe to ſpeake againſt Balaam the prophet. Therfore let no man in perſecution thinke into what daunger the deuel dothe bring, but let hym rather conſider what helpe God dothe geue: Neither let vs be diſcorra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged thorowe mans malice, but let vs ſtrenghten our fayth with goddes pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tection: for aſmuche as euery man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordyng to the Lordes promyſes, and the merites of his owne faythe, ſhall receyue aſmuche helpe of God, as he beleueth to receyue. Neither is ther a ny thyng which the almighty can not bring to paſſe, except the fayth of hym that ſhould receyue dothe decaye and fayle.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>The .xi. Chapter.</head>
               <p>THat it was told aforehand, that the worlde ſhould hate vs, and that it ſhould ſtere vp perſecucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s againſt vs: &amp; that no newe thing hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth
<pb facs="tcp:11414:31"/>peneth nowe vnto chriſtianes, for aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as good men haue ben trobled from the beginning of the world, and the ryghtfull haue ben oppreſſed and ſlayne of the vnrightfull: The Lorde in the Goſpell doeth afore warne and afore ſhewe ſaieng:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Loan.</hi> 15.</note> yf the worlde hate you, knowe ye that it hated me furſt. yf you were of the worlde, the worlde worlde loue that were his owne. But becauſe ye are not of the worlde, but I haue choſen you out of the worlde, therfore the worlde hate you. Remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber the worde whyche I haue ſpoken vnto you: ther is no ſeruaunt greater than his Lorde. yf they haue perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me, they ſhall alſo perſecute you. And agayne he ſayeth:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Loan.</hi> 16.</note> The houre ſhal come, that euery one that ſhal kil you, ſhall thinke him ſelfe to do God ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice. But they ſhall do this, becauſe they haue not knowen the father nor yet me. Theſe thinges haue I ſpoken vnto you, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the houre of them ſhal come, ye maye reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I tolde you. And againe he ſaieth: verely ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely I ſaie vnto you, ye ſhal wepe and lament, but the worlde ſhall reioyce: ye ſhall ſorowe, but your ſorowe ſhall be turned in to ioye. And againe he
<pb facs="tcp:11414:31"/>ſayeth: Theſe thinges haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto you, that ye maye haue peace in me: in the worlde ye ſhall haue trou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble, but be of good cheare, for I haue ouercome the worlde. And agayne whan he was demaunded of his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, what ſhould be the token of hys comming, and of thende of the world,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luc.</hi> 21.</note> he anſwered and ſayd:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mar.</hi> 13.</note> Take hede that noman deceyue you,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 24.</note> for many ſhall come in my name ſaing: I am Chriſt, and ſhall deceyue many. ye ſhal heare of warres, and of the rumours of war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res, take ye hede, and be not troubled: for theſe thinges muſt come to paſſe, but thende is not yet. Nacion ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryſe againſt nacion, and kingdome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt kyngdome, and there ſhalbe honger and earthquakes, and peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences thorowe all places. All theſe are the beginninges of ſorowes.</p>
               <p>Then ſhal they put you to trouble and ſhal kill you, and ye ſhall be hated of all people for my name ſake: And tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall many be offended, &amp; ſhal betraye one an other, and ſhall hate one an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And many falſe prophetes ſhal a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, and deceiue many: and bicauſe of the abundaunce of wickednes, the cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite of many ſhall ware cold, but he y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11414:32"/>ſhall endure vnto thende, the ſame ſhal be ſaffe. And this gladde tydinges of the kingdome, ſhall be preached tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowe all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde for a witneſſe vnto all nacyons: and than ſhall the ende come. Wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore ye ſhall ſee thabo minacion of deſolatyon ſpoken of by Daniel the prophet, ſtanding in the holy place:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Daniel.</hi> 9.</note> let him that reade it, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande it: Than let them that be in Iury flee in to the mountaines: And him which is on the houſe toppe, not com downe to fet any thing out of his houſe: Neither let him which is in the felde, returne backe to fetche his clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes. Wo be in thoſe daies to women with childe, and to them that geue ſucke, but praie ye that your flight be not in the winter, neither on the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both daie. For than ſhall be great tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulacion, ſuche as was not from the beginning of the world to thys tyme, nor ſhalbe: And excepte thoſe dayes ſhould be ſhortned, ther ſhould no fleſh be ſaued: but for the choſen ſake, thoſe dayes ſhall be ſhortned. Then yf any man ſhall ſaye vnto you, Lo here is Chriſt, or ther is Chriſt, beleue it not. For ther ſhall aryſe falſe Chriſtes, and falſe prophetes, and ſhal do great mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles
<pb facs="tcp:11414:32"/>and wonders, In ſomuche that yf it were poſſible, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the choſen per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhould be deceyued. But take you hede, loo I haue tolde you all thynges before. Wherfore yf they ſhal ſaye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, behold he is in the wyldernes, go not forthe. Beholde in the ſerrete places, beleue not. For as the lyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning commeth out of the eaſt, and ſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth into the weſt: So ſhall y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of the ſone of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be. For wherſoeuer a deade carcaſe is, thether wil y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Egles be gathered together. Forthwith after the tribulatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of thoſe dayes the ſune ſhall be darkened, and the Wone ſhall not geue her lyght, &amp; the ſtarres ſhall fall from heauen, and the powers of heauen ſhall moue. And then ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare the ſigne of the Sonne of man in heauen. And then ſhall al the kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reddes of the earthe lament them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and they ſhall ſe the ſonne of man commyng in the cloudes wyth great power and glory. And he ſhall ſende his Angels with great power &amp; glory &amp; with a great trompet. And they ſhall gather together his choſen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the iiij. wyndes, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the one ende of heauen to the other. Neither are theſe thinges which nowe happe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to chriſteans, new
<pb facs="tcp:11414:33"/>or ſodeine: for aſmuche as good &amp; iuſt me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; ſuch as be thorowly bent to kepe the lawe of God, &amp; are afraid to ſtaine the innocency of lyfe &amp; true religion, do alwayes walke the harde &amp; ſtraite waye thorowe trobles &amp; iniuries, and thorowe the greuous &amp; manifolde pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhementes of deadly &amp; malicious em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nities. Thus is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghtfull Abel firſt killed of his brother,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.</note> in the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the worlde,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg.</hi> 14.</note> &amp; Iacob is co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to flye,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 19.</note> &amp; Ioſeph is ſolde: &amp; king Saul perſecuteth the merciful Dauid, &amp; king Achab endeuoureth to oppreſſe Helias, which did conſtantly &amp; man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully defende the maieſtie of God. <g ref="char:dram">ʒ</g>a charias the prieſt is killed betwene the temple &amp; the aulter,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 23.</note> that he myght there be made a ſacrifice him ſelfe, where he had offred ſacrifices. To be ſhorte, ther are very many martirdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of the rightfull, which are often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes celebrate. Ther are very many enſamples of faithe &amp; godlines left for them that ſhal come after. The .iii. chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren Ananias, Ararias, Miſahel, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge equal, in loue of one mynde, in faithe ſtabell, in godlynes conſtaunt, and ſtronger then the fla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>myng fire, and the paynes wherwith they were tormented, openly proclaymed that
<pb facs="tcp:11414:33"/>they ſerued God alone and only, that they knewe hym alone,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dani</hi> 3.</note> that they wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipped him alone, ſaieng: O king Na buchodonoſor, we haue no nede to make the any anſwer in this mater. For God whome we ſerue, is able to deliuer vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hote burning ouen O king, and to ridde vs out of thy han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des: but yf he will not, yet ſhalt thou knowe that we wil not ſerue thy god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, nor do reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ymage which thou haſt ſet vp.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dani.</hi> 14.</note> And the godlye man Daniel full of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy Gooſt cryeth out &amp; ſayeth: I worſhip nothing but only my Lorde, which hath made heauen &amp; earth. Tobias alſo althoughe he was vnder a kingly &amp; tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nous bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dage, yet being fre in vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding &amp; ſpirite co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth God, &amp; do excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d god his power and maieſtie ſaieng:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tobi.</hi> 13.</note> I wil praiſe him in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lande of my captiuitie, &amp; wil ſhewe his power amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges the ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful nacion. But what ſhould I ſpeake of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Machabees whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che do fulfill the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre of .vii. for a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of abſolute ꝑfectnes.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.</note> Theſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen brethren are ſo lincked together in martirdome, as in the diſpoſicion &amp; ordinau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of God, the firſt ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dayes do couteyne ſeuen thouſande yeres:
<pb facs="tcp:11414:34"/>As the ſeuen ſpirites and ſeuen An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels ar aſſiſtant and preſent before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> face of the Lord, And the ſeuen faſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>delſtickes in the tabernacle of witneſſe, And the ſeuen golden can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delſtickes in the reuelacion, And the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pillars in Salomon, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whome wiſdome doeth builde her howſe: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſo the number alſo ther of ſeuen brethren, doeth comprehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in them the number of ſeuen churches: Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as we reade in the firſt boke of kinges, that the barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> brought furthe ſeuen: And in Eſay ſeuen wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take holde vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, after whoſe name they require to benamed: And Paule thapoſtle being myndefull of this lau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full and certaine number, writeth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to ſeuen churches: And in the reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Lord doeth directe his diuine commaundementes, and heuenly pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceptes, to ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> churches, and their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels: The which ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber is now fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de in theſe brethren, that laufull perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon might be fulfilled. With the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſonnes the mother alſo their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and rote is certeinly copled, which afterwardes brought furthe ſeuen churches, herſelfe being tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe goddes voice firſt and alone fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded
<pb facs="tcp:11414:34"/>vpon the rocke. Neither is w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> out miſtery, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> in the martyrdomes y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is founde alone with her ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes. For the martyrs which in their ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringes did teſtefie them ſelues to be the ſonnes of God, ar now cownted to haue none other father but God. As the Lorde in the goſpel teacheth ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng: call no man your father vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 23.</note> for ther is but one your father, which is in heauen. O how glorious confeſſions did they make? Howe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, howe excellent leſſons of faithe haue they geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? The king Antiochus being angery (yea rather Antichriſt re preſented by Antiochus) went about to defile with the filth of ſwines fleſhe the gloriouſe mouthes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> martyrs, which thorowe the ſpirite of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion war inuincible: And when he had gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uouſly beaten them with ſcorges, and yet neuer the neare his purpoſe, he commaunded the frieng pannes or cauldrons to be made hote, in to the which (after they war made hote, and ſet on fire) he commaunded that he which had furſt ſpoken, and had moſt prouoked the king to anger thorowe the conſtancy of godlines and faithe, ſhould be throwen in the fried. But
<pb facs="tcp:11414:35"/>they furſte plucked out hys tonge, whiche had confeſſed God, and cut it of. What martyrdome hathe ther ben more glorious? For the tonge whiche had confeſſed the name of God, ought it ſelfe firſt to go to God. Afterwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des they inuented more bitter puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes for the ſeconde. For before they tormented his other membres. They of a purpoſed hatred againſte God plucte of the ſkinne of his heade with the heares and all. For ſeyng Chriſte is the heade of man, and the heade of Chriſt is God: he that dyd ſo bocherly teare the martyrs heade, did perſecute in the head God and Chriſt. But the martir hoping in his martir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and aſſuring him ſelfe of the rewarde of the reſurrection thoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>we the gifte of God, cryed out and ſayde: Thou thorowe thy power de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeſt vs from this preſent lyfe: but the kyng of the worlde ſhall rayſe vs vp (that are deade for his lawes) in to the eternall reſurrection of lyfe. The thirde beyng demaunded to put forthe his tonge, did it quickely: For he had nowe learned of his brother, to contempne the payne of cutting of
<pb facs="tcp:11414:35"/>the tonge: He did alſo conſtauntlye ſtretche forthe his handes, that they myght be cutte of, and was very hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pye in ſuffering this kynde of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: For aſmuche as it was his fortune wyth ſtretched out handes, to be made like vnto the Lordes paſſion in this ſuffering<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The fourth alſo with like corrage diſpiſing the tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes and anſwering with an heauenly voice to the kinges confuſion, cryed out and ſayde: It is beſte for vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng put to deathe of men, to haue our hope and truſte in God, to be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed agayne of him vnto eternall lyfe. As for thee, thou ſhalt haue no reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection to lyfe. The fyfthe beſydes that thorowe the ſtrenght of faythe he trode vnder the fote the bocherly tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of the king, and many cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el paynes: he was alſo ſtrenghtened thorow Goddes ſpirite to a foreknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lege of thinges to come, and propheci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto the kynge, that bothe the indig nacion of God, and alſo his venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunce wolde ſhortlye folowe vpon him. Thou (ſayeth he) hauynge power amonge men (for thou arte a mortall man alſo thy ſelfe) doeſt what
<pb facs="tcp:11414:36"/>thou wilt. But thinke thou not that Bod hathe forſaken our generacion. Abide the, &amp; behold the great power of God, after what maner he wil tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the and thy ſeade. O what an eaſement was this of martyrdome, howe great, howe excellent was this comforte? In his ſufferinges not to thinke vpon his owne torments, but to tell furthe the puniſhememtes of his tormentor? In the .vi. not only godlines but humilite alſo ought to be comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded in that the martyr cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenged no thing to him ſelfe,<note place="margin">The hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milite of Martyrs.</note> neither did he with proude wordes boſt of the honour of his confeſſion: but did ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther impute vnto his owne ſynnes, that he ſuffred perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the king, and as touching vengaunce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhould folowe, he committed that vnto God. He taught martyrs to be ſhamefaſt, to hope in God for reuengement, and to bragge no thing in their ſufferin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Be not vainely deceiued O king (ſaieth he) For we ſuffer here for our owne ſakes, bicauſe we haue ſynned againſt our God: But thinke not thou to eſcape vnpuniſhed, ſcing y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> haſt atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pted to fight againſt God. The wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der full mother alſo which was neither
<pb facs="tcp:11414:36"/>diſcorraged thorowe the weakenes of the kinde, nor trobled with the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde lacke of children, behelde gladly her ſonnes dieing: neither did ſhe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider their paines, but alſo their glories, and thorow the vertue of her eies, ſhe offered vnto God, as great martyrdome, as did her ſonnes in the ſufferinges &amp; torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of their mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bres. After the ſix war tormented and ſlayne, ther remayned yet one of the brethren, vnto whome the king pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed riches, Lordeſhipe, and many thinges: that at the leſt by ouercom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of one, his fearce crueltye might be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted: &amp; he deſired that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother together w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him,<note place="margin">The xa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of a godly mother.</note> wolde be a meane to ouerthrowe her ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. She intreated her ſonne: But after ſuche ſorte as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a mother of martyrs, as it beca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me one myndeful of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe, &amp; of God: As it became one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loued her ſonnes, not wantonly but ſtrongly. She in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated him in dede, but that was to confeſſe God: She intreated him that he being a brother, ſhoulde not be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from his brethren in the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhipe of praiſe and glory: Than reconning her ſelfe to be a mother of ſeuen ſonnes, yf it might be her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune
<pb facs="tcp:11414:37"/>to bring furthe ſeuen to God, and not to the world. She therfore ar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ming and ſtrenghtning him, &amp; bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againe her ſonne w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> a more happey birthe, ſaied vnto him: O my ſonne haue pitye vpon me that bare the .ix. monethes in my wombe, and gaue the ſucke thre yeres, and nori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed &amp; brought the vp vnto this age: I beſeche the my ſonne loke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earthe, &amp; whan thou haſt con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidered all thinges that are in them, vnderſtande that God made them and mans generacion of nothing. Therfore my ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne feare not this ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, but ſuffer deathe ſtedfaſtly, like as thy brethren haue done: that I maye receiue the againe in the ſame mercy with thy brethren.</p>
               <p>Great is the praiſe of this mother in exhorting to godlynes, but greater was her praiſe in the feare of God, &amp; in the truthe of faithe, bicauſe ſhe war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ranted neither her ſelfe, nor her ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne any parte in the honour of the .vi. martyrs: neither did ſhe beleaue that the praier of the brethren, ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite to the ſaluacion of him that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied. She rather perſuaded him
<pb facs="tcp:11414:37"/>to be partaker with them in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, that in the daye of iudgement he myght be founde among his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren. After theſe thinges the mother dyed alſo together with her children. For this was nowe moſt cumbely for ber, to be ioyned vnto them in the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of glory, whom ſhe had borne and faſhioned to martirdome, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> her ſelfe myght alſo folowe them, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe had before hande ſent vnto God. And that no man ſhould by any deceit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full occaſion offered him, either to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cante, or any other waye embrace the wicked gyft or rewarde of deceyuers: Let vs alſo ſpeake of Eleazarus,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eleazarus</hi> 2. <hi>Mac<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> 6.</note> who hauyng libertie geuen him by the kin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges ſeruauntes, to take ſuche fleſhe as was lawful for him to eate, ſhould but fayne himſelfe to eate of the ſacrifices &amp; vnlawful meates that were brought in, and ſo deceiue the king. He wolde in no wyſe conſent to this deceyte, ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eng: that it became neither his age, nor his noble ſtocke, to fayne himſelfe to do that, wherin many myght be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended and brought into error: Thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that Eleazarus being nynety ye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res olde, had forſaken and betrayed the lawe of God, and were gone to the
<pb facs="tcp:11414:38"/>maners of ſtraungers: Neither dyd he thinke it any worthy matter by of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendyng God,<note place="margin">What they gaine that denye God.</note> and runnyng into the daunger of eternall puniſhement, to gaine the ſhort momentes of this lyfe. And he beyng ther long tormented, &amp; nowe at the point of death, ſighed and ſayd as he dyed amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſtripes and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes: O Lorde which haſt the holy knowlege, thou knoweſt openly, that where as I myght be delyuered from deathe, I ſuffer theſe ſore paynes of my body: but in my mynde I am wel content to ſuffer them, becauſe I fear thee. Certeinly his fayth was ſincere, &amp; true, &amp; his godlynes perfecte &amp; pure ynoughe: which conſydered not the kyng Antiochꝰ but God that is Iuge: and knewe ryght well that it ſhoulde nothyng profyte him to ſaluacion, yf he ſhould mocke and deceyue man, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God (which is the iuge of our conſcience, &amp; ought only to be feared) ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be mocked nor deceyued by any meanes. Yf therfore we do lyue as godly me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſuche as be dedicate vn to God, yf we do walke in the ſelfe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me auncient, and holy fote ſteppes of the iuſte: Let vs go thorowe the ſame enſamples of paynes &amp; ſufferinges,
<pb facs="tcp:11414:38"/>thorowe the ſame martirdomes and paſſions: And let vs reken the glorye of our tyme in this point more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, that wher as the olde enſamples of martirs are numbred: Now after the plenteouſe abundaunce of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and faithe, the chriſtian martyrs can not be numbred. As Iohan wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth in the reuelacion, ſaieng:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apo.</hi> 7.</note> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this I behelde a great multytude which no man could number, of al na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyons &amp; kinredes, people and tonges ſtanding before the ſeate, and before the lambe, and they war clothed with long white garmentes, and they had palmes in their handes, and cried w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> a loude voice ſaieng: Health vnto our God ſitting vpon the ſeate, and vnto the lambe: And one of thelders anſwe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, ſaieng vnto me: what are theſe which are arayed in long white gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, and whence came they? and I ſaied vnto him: Lord thou woteſt. And he ſaied vnto me: Theſe are they which came out of great trybulacion, &amp; they haue waſſhed their garments, and made them white in the blodde of the lambe: Therfore are they in the p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſence of the ſeate of God, &amp; ſerue him daye &amp; night in his te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple. But if it be
<pb facs="tcp:11414:39"/>ſhewed &amp; prowed that the people of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> martyrs are ſo many, no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould thinke it an hard thing, to be a martyr, ſeing he may ꝑceiue, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of martyrs ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be numbred.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>The .xij. chaptre.</head>
               <p>VVhat hope &amp; rewarde abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for the iuſte and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs after the fight and paſſions of this life, the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly goſt hathe ſhewed and folde aforhand by Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaing: And thoughe they ſuffer tormentes before men,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sapi.</hi> 3.</note> yet is their hope full of Immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talite. And although they be puniſhed in fewe thinges, yet in many thinges ſhal they be well rewarded. For God hathe proued them and founde them mete for him ſelfe. Yea as the gold in the fornace he doeth trie them, and receiueth them as a burnte offering, and whan the tyme co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, they ſhal be loked vpon. They ſhal Iuge the na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cions and haue dominion ouer the people, and their Lord ſhal reigne for euer. In likemaner the ſame Salamo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doeth deſcribe the vengaunce y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> God ſhall take for our cauſe, and ſetteth
<pb facs="tcp:11414:39"/>forthe the penaunce or ſorowe of our perſecutours and enemyes ſaieng: Then ſhall the righteouſe ſtande in great ſtedfaſtneſſe, againſt ſuche as haue dealt extremely with them,<note place="margin">Sapi. <hi>5.</hi> The late repentau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of them that be in hell.</note> and taken awaye their labours. When they ſe it, they ſhalbe vexed with hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible feare, and ſhal wonder at the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines of the ſodayne healthe, groning for very diſtres of mynde, and ſhal ſay within them ſelues hauyng inwarde ſorowes, and mournyng for very an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhe of mynde. Theſe are they who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſomtyme had in deriſion, and ieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced vpon. We fooles thought their life very madnes, and their ende to be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out honour. Howe then are they cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted among the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God, &amp; their porcion among the ſaintes: Therfore we haue erred fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the waye of truthe, and the lyght of ryghtfulnes hath not ſhyned ouer vs, and the Sunne of vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtanding roſe not vp vpon vs. We haue weried our ſelues in the waye of wyckednes and deſtruction. Tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe wayes haue we gone: but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waye of the Lorde we haue not knowen. What good hathe our pryde done vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs? Or what ꝓfite hath the pompe of ryches brought vs? all thoſe thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges
<pb facs="tcp:11414:40"/>are paſſed awaye like a ſhadowe. In likemaner in .<hi>115.</hi> pſalme the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of martyrdome is declared,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.</note> wheare he ſaieth: preciouſe is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deathe of his ſaintes in the ſight of the Lord.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 125.</note> Likewiſe alſo in. <hi>125.</hi> is expreſſed bothe our ſorowfull affliction and alſo our ioyeful rewarde, wher he ſaieth: They that ſowe in teares, ſhal reape w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> ioye. They went furthe, wandering and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing their ſeades with weping: But they ſhal com againe with ioye, takig vp their lappes. And againe in the <hi>118.</hi> pſalme, he ſaieth, bleſſed are thoſe that be vndefiled in the waie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118.</note> which walke in the lawe of the Lord: Bleſſed are thoſe that ſearche out his witneſſes, &amp; and ſeke him with their hole hart. Fur thermore the Lord which is the ſelfe reuengar of our perſecucion, and the rewarder of our ſufferinge, ſaieth in the goſpell: happye ſhall they be which ſhall ſuffer perſecutyon for rightouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſake,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Math.</hi> 5.</note> bicauſe the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen is theirs: And againe he ſaieth: bleſſed ſhall ye be, whan me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall hate you, and ſhall ſeperate and throwe you out, and ſhal curſe your name as wicked for the ſonne of mans ſake, be gladde in that daie and reioyce, For
<pb facs="tcp:11414:40"/>lo your rewarde is great in heauen. And agayne: he that loſeth his liffe for me ſhall ſaue it. Neither are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of Goddes promiſe laid vp only for ſuche as be tormented and ſayne: For although the faithful be not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte to the very ſuffering, yet if faithe abide perfecre &amp; not ouercome, if the thriſtian (deſpiſing and forſaking all thinges that at his owne) ſhall ſhewe him ſelf to folow Chriſt, he alſo is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored of Chriſt among the martyrs by his owne promiſe, wher he ſaieth: ther is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that forſaketh houſe or fielde, or father and mother, or breth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, or wiffe, or ſonnes, for the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God, which do not receiue ſeuen tymes as muche in this world, and in the world to come eternal liffe. In likemaner in the reuelacion he ſpeaketh the ſame thing ſaie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apo.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.</note> and I ſawe the ſowles of them that wer kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led for the name of Ieſu &amp; the worde of God: And whan he had made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon firſt of them that war ſlayne, he added ſaieng: &amp; who ſo euer haue not worſhipped the Image of the beſt, neither receiued his marke vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their forhedes, or on their handes: Al which being ſen of him at once in one place,
<pb facs="tcp:11414:41"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11414:41"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11414:42"/>he coppleth together ſayeng: And they liued and reigned with Chriſt. He ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth, that they all do lyue and reigne with Chriſt: not only they that were ſlayne, but all ſuche alſo as ſtanding manfully in the ſtedfaſtneſſe of their faythe, and in the feare of God, haue not worſhipped the ymage of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beaſt, neither haue conſented vnto them in their haynous and cruell proclamaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; lawes. That we ſhall receyue more in rewarde of our ſuffeting, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are the paynes and afflictions whiche we nowe endure, the bleſſed Apoſtle Paule dothe proue (which beyng tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe goddes fauour taken vp into the thirde heauen &amp; into paradiſe,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.</note> wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſeth that he herde wordes that can not be vttered, which glorieth, that he had (thorowe ſecrete faythe) ſene Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt: which hauyng certeine knowlege of the truth, profeſſeth that which he had bothe learned, &amp; ſeen) ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eng: The afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of this lyfe are not worthy y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> glorye, which ſhalbe ſhewed vpon vs.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rous.</hi> 8.</note> Who is it nowe that will not labour with all his ſtrenght to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne ſo great glory, that he maye be made the frende of God, and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly reioyce with Chriſt: That after
<pb facs="tcp:11414:42"/>theſe worldly tormentes and paynes, he may come to the diuine and heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rewardes? Yf the ſouldears of this worlde thinke it a glorious matter, (after they haue oucrcome thennemy) to returne into their cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trey with tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphe: howe muche more noble and excellent a thing is it, after we haue ouercome the deuel, to returne into pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>radiſe triumphing? And (he beyng ſubdued, which before deceyued) to beare with vs the tokens of victorye into that place, from the which fynful Adam was caſt out? To offer vnto God a moſt acceptable ſacerfice, that is an vndefiled faythe, the ſounde ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue of the mynde, the bright prayſe of godlines? To folowe him,<note place="margin">A deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of the glori of eternall liffe.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhal come to take vengeaunce of his eune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes? To ſyt on his ſyde, when he ſhall ſyt to iuge? To be made an heire an nexed with Chriſt? To be made equall vnto the Angels? To reiuyſe together with the patriarkes, Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les and prophetes in the poſſeſſion of the heauenly kyngdome? What per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecucion can ouercome, what tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes can ouerthrowe theſe cogita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cions and thoughtes?</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:11414:43"/>
               <p>The mynde that is grownded vpon godly meditacions, abideth ſtrong &amp; ſtable: And he whoſe hart is ſtrenght<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned with a certeine and ſounde faithe of thinges to come, ſtandeth immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueable againſt al the terrors of the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uell, and threatninges of the worlde. The eyes ar ſhutte vp in the perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the world, neuertheles heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is opened: Antichriſt doeth threaten, but yet the Lord Chriſt doeth defende: deathe is brought in, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding immortalite doeth folowe after: The world is viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly pluct from him that is ſlayne: Neuerthles paradiſe is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to him that is reſtored. The tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall life is deſtroied, but yet the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall is repaired. O how great is the dignue, how great is the ſaffety to departe hence Ioyfully, to departe hence gloryouſly among afflictyons and tormentes? In a moment to cloſe vp theyes, wherwith men and the world war ſeen: and immediatly to open againe the ſame to beholde god and Chriſt? O how ſwift is this departure, to be conueied fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thearthe ſodenly, and to be ſituate and placed in the celeſtical &amp; heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly kingdome? Theſe thinges ought to be conſidered
<pb facs="tcp:11414:43"/>in our hartes and myndes, vpon the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe thinges ought we to ſtudy &amp; muſe bothe night and daie. yf the daie of the perſecuting of Chriſt ſhall finde ſuche a ſowldear: the vertue which is redy for the rewarde can not be ouer come. Or if he ſhal be preuented &amp; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led hence before: the faithe which was redy vnto martyrdome, ſhall not be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out rewarde. Rewarde is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (God being iudge) w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out hinderance of tyme. In ꝑ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution the ſowldear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, in peace the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is crowned (God being iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge) Amen.</p>
               <p>Thende of thebofe of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortacion to marur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:11414:44"/>
            <head>Thargument of the <hi>Epiſtle folowing.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">By this Epiſtle S. Cipriane ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth the people that dwelt at Thibaris to fepe and endure in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt with a pure mynde, perfit fayth, and Godlye deuocion.</head>
            <p>Cipria<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto the people of Thibaris. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>THad decreed, and was fully pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed moſt dearely beloued bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thren (yf the ſtate of thynges, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenient tyme wolde haue geuen lyberty) to haue come my ſelfe vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to you (according as you haue ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyred) &amp; (beyng preſent) to haue ther ſtrenghtned the brotherhed with our exhortacion to the vtter moſt of our po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer.<note place="margin">The Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of a true bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhope.</note> But foraſmuche as thorough vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent &amp; great buſynes we are thus w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden &amp; letted, that we haue no lyber<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye to go farre fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence, &amp; to be long abſent from the people, which thorowe goddes mercy is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to our go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: I haue in the meane tyme ſent you theſe letters in my ſtede and
<pb facs="tcp:11414:44"/>rowme. For it is our deutye (ſeyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lorde dothe vouche ſaue often tymes to pricke vs forewarde &amp; to admoniſh vs) to extende forth the care of our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction &amp; warning vnto your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence alſo. For ye ought to knowe, &amp; for a certeintie to beleue &amp; holde, that the day of troble beginneth to houer ouer ouer heades, &amp; that thende of the world &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme of Antichriſt draweth neare, that we al may ſtande ready to the bat taile,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioan.</hi> 2.</note> &amp; that we thinke vpon nothing but only of the glory of eteruall lyfe, &amp; the crowne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhalbe geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the Lorde: Neither let vs thinke, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thinges co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming are ſuche as ar alredy paſſed. A more dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerus &amp; cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eller fight houereth now ouer vs, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which Chriſt his ſouldiers ought to prepare the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> an vncorrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted faith, &amp; ſtrong vertue:<note place="margin">the laye peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple dranke the cuppe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes bloode in Cipriae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes tyme <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> To<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſidering y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they do therfore daily drinke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cup of the blodde of Chriſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they maye alſo ſhede their blodde for Chriſt his ſake. For this is to deſire to be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de wyth Chriſt, to folowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which Chriſt bothe taught and dyd, according to the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng of Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thapoſtle: he that ſayeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he abydeth in Chriſte, ought alſo to walk after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame maner y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he walked
<pb facs="tcp:11414:45"/>In like maner exhorteth &amp; teacheth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed apoſtle Paule ſaieng,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> we ar the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes of God: but it we be ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, than are we alſo heires, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heires I meane of God, and heires annexed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt: yf we ſuffer together w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, that we may be alſo glorified together w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him. Al theſe thinges ought to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered of vs at this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould deſire any thing of the worlde, which is now in dyeng: but might folowe Chriſt, which bothe liueth him ſelfe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtingly, &amp; alſo maketh aliue his ſeruauntes that abide in the faithe of his name. For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme is come moſt dearely beloued brethren, which our Lord long ſins warned vs of, &amp; tolde vs aforehand that it wold com ſaieng: The howre ſhall com,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 16.</note> that whoſoeuer ſhall kill you, will thinke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he doeth God ſeruice. But theſe thiges wil they do, bicauſe they haue not knowen the father neither yet me. Theſe thinges haue &amp; tolde you, that whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> howre of them is come, ye might remember y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> I tolde you. Let no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therfore mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel, that we are exceadingly trobled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinual ꝑſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tymes vexed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> paineful trobles, ſeing that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord tolde aforeha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> theſe ſhould happen
<pb facs="tcp:11414:45"/>in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt daies &amp; w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine &amp; exhorta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of his worde inſtructed &amp; prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red our fight &amp; warrefare. Peter alſo his apoſtle taught, that perſecutions do therfore happen, that we maye be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tried, and that we thorowe deathe and ſufferinges myght alſo be ioyned and knitte to the loue of God, after then<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample of the iuſte men that went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs: For in his epiſtle he wryteth thus, ſayeng: Dearely beloued won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der not at this heate that is happened vnto you:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.</note> which is come among you to trie you. Neither fall ye awaye as thoughe a newe thing had chaunced vnto you: but as ofte as ye are parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of Chriſtes paſſions reioyce in al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thinges, that when his glorye appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, ye may alſo be mery and gladde. yf ye be rayled vpon for the name of Chriſt, happie are ye: For the name of the maieſtye and power of God dothe reſte in you. Which verely is blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of them, but is glorifyed of you. Thapoſtles haue alſo taught vs ſuche thinges, as they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues did learne of the Lordes preceptes and heauenly commaundementes, the Lorde hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe ſtrenghtning vs and ſayeng:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luce.</hi> 18. <hi>Math.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Ther is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſayeth he) that leaueth houſe, or felde, other father and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:11414:46"/>other betherne, or ſuſters, other wife or children for the kingdome of goddes ſake, which ſhall not receiue ſeuen tymes as muche in this world, and in the world to cum life euerlaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. And againe, bleſſed ſhal ye be (ſaith he) when men ſhal hate you, and ſhal excommunicate and ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>niſhe you,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.</note> and ſhall curſe your name as wicked for the ſonne of mans ſake: reioyce and be gladde in that daie, for your re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde is great in heauen. The Lorde wold haue vs to be mery and ioyeful in perſecutions: For in the tyme of perſecution the crownes of faithe are diſtributed and geuen: than are God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſowldears tried. Than do heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s open vnto the martyrs. For we haue not after ſuche maner profeſſed ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dearfare, that we ſhould thinke vpon peace only, and ſhould refuſe and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the fight: Foraſmuche as the Lord, the maſtre of humilite, patience and ſufferaunce hathe himſelfe wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in the ſelfe ſame ſouldearfare, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he might firſt do that thing himſelfe, which he taught to be obſerued of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and might himſelfe firſt ſuffer for vs that, which he exhorted vs to ſuffer. Set allwaies before your eies
<pb facs="tcp:11414:46"/>dearely beloued, that he (which alone hathe receiued al iugement of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp; whichſhal com to iuge all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) hathe euennow aforehand pronoun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ced the ſentence of his Ingement and knowlage to come,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 10</note> ſhewing aforeha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d &amp; witneſſing, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he will confeſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his father, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe him, &amp; will denye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> denye him. Yf we might auoide &amp; eſcape death,<note place="margin">No man can eſcape death.</note> we might iuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feare to die: but ſeing that of neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mortall muſt die, let vs embrace thoccaſion which God by his promiſe hathe voucheſaued to offer vs: And let vs ſo ende our life that we maye receiue the rewarde of immortalite: Neither let vs be afraide to be ſlaine, ſeing yt ys manifeſt that we are then crowned, when we are ſlaine and kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Neither let any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moſt dearely beloued brethren betrobled,<note place="margin">Flight for feare of perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </note> whan he ſhall ſe our people driuen awaie &amp; ſcatered thorowe the feare of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon and ſhall not ſee the brotherhede gathered together, nor heare the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes preache and declare the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.<note place="margin">S. Cipria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne vſeth, this worde brother heads</note> We vnto whom it is not lauful to kill, but muſt of neceſſite be killed, can not than be al gathered together.
<pb facs="tcp:11414:47"/>Wherſoeuer any of the brethren ſhall in thoſe dayes be for a ſeaſon ſeperate from the flocke in body and not in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite thorow the neceſſitie of the tyme, let him not be troubled thorowe the terribleneſſe of that fleing: neither let him be afrayd, when he departeth to hyde himſelfe in the wilſome wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: For he is not alone, which hathe Chriſt to his companion in fleing: He is not alone, which keping the temple of God, is not without God, wherſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he ſhall happen to be. And yf the theſe and murtherer ſhal deſtroye the, as thou arte fleyng into the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and mountaynes, yf the wilde beſt ſhall aſſaile the, yf hunger, thurſt, or colde ſhall pinche the, or yf the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt or ſtorme ſhall drowne the, when thou doeſt by ſee haſtely flee awaye, Chriſt abydeth and loketh for his ſoul dear wherſoeuer he fyghteth: And he geueth vnto him (that dyeth for the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nour of his name in the tyme of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution) that rewarde,<note place="margin">A com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort for ſuche as are preue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pined &amp; murdered in preſons</note> which he hath promiſed to gyue in the reſurrection. Neither is the glory of martirdome any whit the leſſe, thoughe a man dye not openly amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g many, when Chriſt his cauſe was thoccaſion of his death.
<pb facs="tcp:11414:47"/>For he is a ſufficient witneſſe of his martirdome, that tryeth martirs and crowneth them.<note place="margin">Abel.</note> Let vs moſt dearely beloued brethren folowe the ryghtful Abel, which beganne and conſecrated martirdomes, when he was the firſt that was ſlayne for ryghtfulnes ſake. Let vs folowe Abraham the frende of God,<note place="margin">Abraham</note> which delaied not to offer vp his ſonne in ſacrifice with his owne han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, when thorowe a deuouce fayth he obeyed God. Let vs folowe the thre children Ananias, Azarias, and Miſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hel, which being nether feared thorow their tender age, nor diſcorraged tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row captiuitie (whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iury &amp; Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were ouercome &amp; take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) ouercame by the power of faythe the kyng in his owne kingdome. Which beyng com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to worſhip the ymage that Nabuchodonoſor hade made, ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came bothe the kynges threatninges and the flamyng fyre, Crieng out and teſtefieng their faith w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> theſe wordes:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dani.</hi> 3.</note> We haue no nede O king Nabucho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donoſor to make the any aunſwer tou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching this mater. For ther is a God whome we ſerue able to delyuer vs from the fornace of the burnyng fire, and he ſhall delyuer vs O king from
<pb facs="tcp:11414:48"/>thy handes: but if he do not, let it be knowen vnto the, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> we will not ſerue thy goddes, neither wil we worſhippe the golden ymage, which thou haſt ſet vp. They beleaued that thorowe faith they might eſcape, neuertheles they added (but if he do not) that the king might be certefied, that they war alſo able to die for Goddes ſake, whome they worſhipped. For this is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of faithe and vertue, to beleaue and knowe, that God is able to deliuer fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> preſent deathe: &amp; yet neither to feare nor giue place to deathe, that faithe maie be tried the better. Out of theyr mouth brake furth the vndefiled &amp; in uincible ſtrenght of the holy gooſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the wordes which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord ſpake in his goſpel, might appeare to be true: wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhall laie ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des on you (ſaithe he) be not carefull what ye ſhall ſpeake. For it ſhal be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you in that howre, what ye ſhall ſpeake.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 10</note> For it is not you which do ſpeake, but the ſpirite of the father that ſpeaketh in you. He hathe promiſed, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yt ſhal be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; offerd vs of God in that houre, what we maye ſpeake: And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is not we y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpeake, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father: which (foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muche as he neither departeth, nor is
<pb facs="tcp:11414:48"/>ſeparated from them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> confeſſe) doeth bothe ſpeake, &amp; ys crowned in vs. In likemaner Daniel whan he was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to worſhip y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Idol Bel (whome bothe the king &amp; people did than wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe) in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defence of the honour of his God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dani.</hi> 14.</note> be brake out with the full li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berte of faithe, ſaie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g: I worſhippeno thing but only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord my God, which hathe made heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and earthe.<note place="margin">The ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabeis.</note> What ſhould I ſpeake of the bitter torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of the bleſſed martyrs in the Macha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beis, &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> manifolde paines of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vn. brethren, &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother that did bothe 01 comforte her children in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, &amp; died alſo hereſelf with them? Are not ther doctrines of great vertue &amp; faithe witneſſed? And do they not exhorte vs alſo thorowe their paſſions vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> triumphe of martirdome?<note place="margin">The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes Thapoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels. what we ought to learne at the death of good men. Mat. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> What ſhal I ſpeake of the prophetes, whome the ſpirite hathe incorraged vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>age of thinges to come? What ſhall I ſaie of thapoſtles, whome the Lord hathe choſen? Haue not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inſte, (wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they are ſlaine for rightfulnes ſake) taught vs alſo to dye? The birthe of Chriſt beganne ſtraite waies with the martyrdome of infantes and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes: that ſo many as war two yeares
<pb facs="tcp:11414:49"/>olde and vnder, were ſlayne for his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ſake. The age that was not yet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for the bataile, was neuertheles mete to receiue the crowne: &amp; that they might appear * to be innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes,<note place="margin">Or, it might ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare.</note> which are ſlayne for Chriſt, the innocent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancye &amp; childhode was killed for his name ſake. It is nowe declared that no man is free from the daunger of perſecucio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſeyng that ſuche lytleones haue ſuffered martirdome. What rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſonable cauſe can any chriſtian man haue,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> haue no excuſe.</note> that wil not (beyng a ſeruaunt) ſuffer, ſeyng the Lorde himſelfe hathe firſt ſuffered: And that we wyl not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer for our owne ſynnes, when he (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng no ſynne of his owne) hath ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered for vs? The ſonne of God hathe ſuffered, to make vs goddes ſonnes: And wyl not the ſonne of man ſuffer. that he maie contynue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne of God? Yf we be hated of the worlde, the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered of the world chriſt ſuffered firſt. Yf we ſuffer reuiling wordes in this worlde, if we be driuen to flee, yf we indure tormentes, the maker &amp; Lorde of the worlde haue taſted of more gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſe paines: who alſo warneth vs ſaing: Yf the worlde (ſaith he) hate you,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 15.</note> remember that yt hated me firſt.
<pb facs="tcp:11414:49"/>Yf you war of the world, the worlde wolde loue that which war his owne.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 15.</note> But bicauſe ye are not of the worlde, but I haue choſen you out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world, therfore doeth the world hate you. Reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber the worde which I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken vnto you: ther is no ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Lorde. Yf they haue perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me, they ſhall alſo perſecute you. The Lord and our God hathe perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and done whatſoeuer he taught: and can the diſciple and ſcollar be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed that learneth, &amp; yet doeth not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly? Let none of you dearely be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loued brethren be ſo feared with the feare of perſecutyon to come, or with the comming of Antichriſt that houe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth ouer our heades, that he ſhould not be founde armed at all pointes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thexortacions of the goſpel, and with the heauenly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninges. Antichriſt is come, but Chriſt wil alſo ſode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him. The en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy murdereth and is very cruell, but the Lord doeth by and by folowe to reuenge our afflictions &amp; wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des. The enemy is a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gry &amp; threatneth, but ther is one that can deliuer vs out of his handes. He ought to be feared, whoſe yre &amp; ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſcape,
<pb facs="tcp:11414:50"/>according as he him ſelfe warneth &amp; ſayeth: Feare ye not them that kill the body, but the ſowle they can not kill.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.</note> But feare him rather, that is able to deſtroie bothe ſowle and body in to hell.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 12.</note> And againe he ſaithe: he that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth his life, ſhal loſe it, &amp; he that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth his life in this worlde, ſhal keape yt vnto eternall life. And in the reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacion he inſtructeth and warneth vs ſaing:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Apo.</hi> 14.</note> yf any man worſhipe the beſt and his image, and taketh his marke in his forehed and in his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, he ſhall alſo drinke of the wine of the wrathe of God, mingeled in the cuppe of his wrathe: and he ſhal be punniſhed with fire and brymſtone in the preſence of the holy angels, and in the preſence of the lambe: And the ſmoke of their tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes goeth vp world withoute ende: Neither ſhall any of them that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe the beſt, and his image, haue any reſt either daie or night. Vnto a temporal and world <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ight, men at bothe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, and they counte it great glory &amp; honoure, yf it maie be their chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to be crowned in the preſence of the people, &amp; in the preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of themperor. Beholde the highe and noble fight,
<pb facs="tcp:11414:50"/>which ys beutified with an heauenly crowne, wher as god maye loke vpon vs fighting: and that he caſting his eyes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whome he hathe vouche ſaued to make his childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, maye haue a pleſaunt beholding and ſpectacle of of our battaile. Whan we warre and fight with the armor of faithe, God lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>keth vpon vs, his angels do beholde vs, &amp; Chriſt doeth approue vs. What worthye glory is it, howe great felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te and happines, to fight ther whear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as God is the defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dar, and to be crow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned ther whearas Chriſt is iuge? Let vs arme our ſelues moſt dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued brethren with all our ſtrenght, &amp; let vs be prepared and made redy to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> battaile with an vncorrupted mynde, with a perfecte faithe, and with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoute vertue. Let the armyes of God marche on and go forewarde vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bataille, that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tched againſt them. Let the perfecte man be armed, that the perfecte loſe not his late conſra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy. Let the fallen be alſo armed, that the falle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maye receuie againe that which be had lou. Let honour prouoke the perfecte, let ſorowe prouoke the fallen vnto the fight and battaile. The bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Apoſtle doeth arme and prepare
<pb facs="tcp:11414:51"/>vs to the fight ſaieng: we wraſtle not againſt fleſhe and blodde,<note place="margin">Ephe. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> but againſt powres, &amp; againſt the rulars of this darkenes of this worlde, againſt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual wickednes in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly thinges. Put you on therfore all the armor of God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ye may be able to reſiſte in the moſt wicked daye, that whan ye haue performed al thinges, ye may ſtande, hauing your loynes girded with the truthe,<note place="margin">The ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mor and weapons of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> &amp; clothed with the breſt plate of rightfulnes, and ſhodde, that ye maye be redy to the goſpel of peace: ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king vp the ſhilde of faithe, wherby ye maye quenche all the firy dartes of the deuel, and take the helmet of healthe, and the ſworde of the ſpirite, which is the worde of God. Let vs put on theſe armowres, let vs fortifie our ſelues with theſe ſpiritual and heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defences, that we maye be able in the moſt wicked daie to reſiſte, and beate backe the deuels threatninges. Let vs put on the breſt plate of right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, that our breſt maye be defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and ſaued againſt the dartes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ennemye. Let vs be ſhodde thorowe the doctrine of the Goſpell, and haue our fete armed, that when we ſhal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to treade and thurſt downe the
<pb facs="tcp:11414:51"/>ſerpent, he maye not be able to byte &amp; ouerthrowe vs. Let vs manfully bear the ſhylde of faythe, by whoſe defence, what ſoeuer the ennemye throweth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs may be quenched. Let vs al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo take the helmet of ſaluacion to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer our heades,<note place="margin">How eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber and parte of the body muſt be armed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> that our eares may be defended, that they maye not heare nor geue hede vnto cruell proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and lawes. Let our eyes be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiyed, that they beholde not the dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable and abhominable ymages. Let our forehed be fenſed, that the marke of God may be kept ſafe. Let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth be armed, that the myghtye conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring tonge may acknowlege and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe her Lord Chriſt. Let vs alſo arme the ryght hande w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſpiritual ſworde,<note place="margin">In Cipriae<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes tyme the people receiued the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in their right han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des.</note> that it maye manfully contemne and deſpiſe the vncleane and wicked ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, that that which hathe receyued the Lordes body, being mindful of the thankes geuing, maye in the ſame em<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brace her Lord, which ſhal after of the ſame her Lorde receyue the rewarde of an heauenly crowne. O howe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and great a daye is that, that is comming moſte dearely beloued bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, when the Lorde ſhal beginne to numbre his people, and by his diuine
<pb facs="tcp:11414:52"/>knowlege to examine the workes of euery one, to ſende the gylty into hell, and to conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne our perſecutours vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a perpetuall burning in the payne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full flame: but vnto vs to re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde of faythe and godlynes. What maner of glorye ſhal that be, and how great gladnes, to be admitted to ſee goddes honour, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou maiſt receaue with Chriſt the Lord thy God the ioye of euerlaſting healthe and lyght? To ſalute Abraham, Iſaac, and Iacob, all the Patriarkes and Prophetes, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, &amp; Martyrs? To reioyce in the delectacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the gyft of immortalitie, with the iuſte men and fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of God in the kingdome of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? To receiue that ther, which neither eye hath ſeen neyther eare hath herde,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</note> nor hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into the harte of man? For tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle teacheth that we ſhall receyue greater rewarde, then either our wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes or afflictions here can deſerue, ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eng: The afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of this lyfe are not worthy of the glory,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.</note> which ſhalbe ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed vpon vs. When the ſhewyng of this glorye ſhall come, when the chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of God ſhal ſhyne ouer vs, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal we be happy &amp; mery, being in honour thorow the goodnes of the Lorde. But alas</p>
            <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
               <desc>〈…〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:11414:52"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
